<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Godly adversity far better than wicked prosperity, or, The rage of the wicked, should not hinder the race of the Godly being a few comfortable reasons or encouragements against the fear and terrour of man : very seasonable &amp; sutable [sic] for the consideration of God's people in this day of tryal, to fortifie them against all troubles and oppositions whatsoever : together with a heavenly discourse concerning the saints in their kingdom, wherein is discovered the excellency of the kingdom itself, and the wonderful glory and happiness of the saints in their heavenly habitation / by Edward Noble ...</title>
            <author>Noble, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1197</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4611</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13081208</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13081208</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97238</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52375)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97238)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 747:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Godly adversity far better than wicked prosperity, or, The rage of the wicked, should not hinder the race of the Godly being a few comfortable reasons or encouragements against the fear and terrour of man : very seasonable &amp; sutable [sic] for the consideration of God's people in this day of tryal, to fortifie them against all troubles and oppositions whatsoever : together with a heavenly discourse concerning the saints in their kingdom, wherein is discovered the excellency of the kingdom itself, and the wonderful glory and happiness of the saints in their heavenly habitation / by Edward Noble ...</title>
                  <author>Noble, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S. Dover ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Inspiration.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97238:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97238:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GODLY ADVERSITY Far better than WICKED PROSPERITY: OR, The Rage of the Wicked, ſhould not Hinder the Race of the Godly.</p>
            <p>Being a few Comfortable <hi>Reaſons</hi> or <hi>Encouragements</hi> againſt the Fear and Terrour of Man: Very Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable &amp; Sutable for the Conſideration of God's People in this Day of Tryal, to Fortifie them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Troubles and Oppoſitions whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Together with a Heavenly Diſcourſe concerning the Saints in their Kingdom; Wherein is Diſcovered the Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Kingdom it ſelf; and the Wonderful Glory and Happineſs of the Saints in their Heavenly Habitation.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Edward Noble,</hi> an unworthy Servant and Priſoner of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 41.14.</hi>
               </bibl> Fear not thou, Worm <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the few Men of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> I will help thee, ſaith the Lord.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 2.10.</hi>
               </bibl> Fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt Suffer; Behold the Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into Priſon, that ye may be Tryed: And ye ſhall have Tribulation certain Dayes: But be thou Faithful unto Death, and thou ſhalt receive a Crown of Life.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 5.10.</hi>
               </bibl> Bleſſed are they which are Perſecuted for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſake, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>S. Dover</hi> in <hi>Chriſtophers Alley</hi> in <hi>Martins,</hi> near <hi>Alderſgatè,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97238:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97238:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To his Dear and much Reſpected Father (according to the fleſh)</hi> FRANCIS NOBLE, <hi>one of the Lords faithful Servants, and Stewards of his Houſhold: And one of the Right Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Society of Saints, in the Faith of the</hi> GOSPEL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear and Well-beloved Father,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NOt only the Bonds of Nature, and the knot of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation betwixt us, but alſo the great Cord of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and Chriſtianity, hath drawn me forth, and induced me to Dedicate theſe my weak fruits of <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> unto your ſerious and pious Conſideration: judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it may be a great Manifeſtation of my Duty towards you, and a ſignal Token of that <hi>tender Love</hi> and <hi>Reſpect,</hi> which your Deſerts (through Grace) calls for at my hands: It is not Silver nor Gold, Money nor Riches that I have here to preſent unto you or to accommodate you withal; but ſuch as my Heavenly Father hath (out of his abundant trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures) beſtowed upon me: It is not <hi>Earthly ſhadows of a Temporal Concernment,</hi> but <hi>Heavenly Subſtance of a Spiritual Nature;</hi> Therefore what I have Received, I freely and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially impart unto you, hoping it will be an acceptable To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto you. Your <hi>Aged Years</hi> I Honour, and your <hi>Gray Hairs</hi> I Reverence, eſpecially being found in the Path of Righteouſneſs: for give me leave to tell you, that it's <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> that makes <hi>Age</hi> truly Honourable and Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, more than Treaſures of Riches, where Godlineſs is wanting. It's no ſmall Joy unto me, when I Conſider you,
<pb facs="tcp:97238:3"/>not only as <hi>my Father in the fleſh,</hi> but alſo <hi>Related to me in the Spirit;</hi> That there is a <hi>nearer Relation</hi> betwixt us than what is <hi>outward,</hi> and a more excellent <hi>Affinity</hi> between us than that of <hi>Nature;</hi> Our <hi>Natural Relations</hi> are but ſhadows and husks, and of a momentary ſtanding; but <hi>Spiritual Affinity</hi> is a fountain of Joy that abides for ever; the <hi>former</hi> will pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and ceaſe from <hi>being,</hi> but the <hi>latter</hi> ſhall continue, and never have an <hi>end.</hi> It's matter of great Rejoycing to me, when I Conſider how you preſs forward and perſevere in the wayes of God, even to your <hi>latter dayes,</hi> and in the midſt of <hi>Troubles,</hi> that you are not frighted from the <hi>Truth,</hi> by the frowns of men, but ſtill you continue faithful to the <hi>Purity of the Goſpel,</hi> notwithſtanding the <hi>threatning ruine</hi> and <hi>ſpoil</hi> that attends it. Oh! how many have run well in their <hi>young dayes,</hi> and gone on eminently for God in a Day of <hi>Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and yet in the time of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> or elſe in the time of <hi>old Age</hi> have grown weary of God, and declined his wayes and Worſhip; and have minded their own eaſe and Intereſt, more than the Glory of God! But bleſſed be the Lord, it's otherwiſe with you, it is not <hi>length of time</hi> that hath dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed your <hi>Love to God;</hi> nor Changes of <hi>Providences</hi> that hath abated your zeal to the <hi>Truth,</hi> nor Alterations in Church and State, that hath altered your Reſolutions in the Work and Service of your <hi>Heavenly Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear Father:</hi> You have lived to behold ſundry and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> of God, and you have ſeen much of the <hi>out-goings</hi> and <hi>in-comings of the Lord</hi> in this Land of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity; and you have experienced much of the Power and Goodneſs of mighty <hi>Jehovah</hi> in ſeveral Conditions, both in <hi>Proſperity</hi> and <hi>Adverſity,</hi> in <hi>Sickneſs</hi> and in <hi>Health;</hi> yea, in the midſt of <hi>Diſcouragements,</hi> you have received <hi>Comforts</hi> from God; and in the midſt of <hi>Troubles,</hi> you have received <hi>Strength</hi> from the Lord: You have ſeen the <hi>Churches of
<pb facs="tcp:97238:3"/>Chriſt</hi> flouriſhing and ſhining in theſe Nations, and the <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> thereof confounded and brought to ſhame: Your eyes have beheld what a Wall of Defence the <hi>Rock of Ages</hi> hath been to his People, and how he hath made their Enemies (though more and Mightier) to become Tributary and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to them; and how he had placed men fearing God, in great Places of Truſt; and thoſe that followed Vertue and Piety, in Places of great Affairs; by which means <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy</hi> became a Terrour to evil-doers, &amp; a Praiſe to them that did well; and <hi>Religion, Vertue</hi> and <hi>Holineſs</hi> was Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced, Upheld and Maintained by a face of <hi>Authority</hi> in theſe Nations, in <hi>your dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now you have lived to ſee <hi>a mighty Change,</hi> and a <hi>wonderful Alteration,</hi> another World (as it were) flowing with ſin and Iniquity, wherein the <hi>Church of Chriſt</hi> is very <hi>low, poor</hi> and <hi>contemptible;</hi> and the <hi>Vineyard of our God</hi> hath been laid open to <hi>ravenous Beaſts,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Boar out of the Wood</hi> hath laid it <hi>waſte;</hi> and they have through their <hi>Subtilty</hi> cauſed many <hi>tall Cedars to fall,</hi> and by their Power have Cruſhed and Oppreſſed the <hi>tender Plants</hi> and <hi>Vines,</hi> and a great Inundation of Sin and Prophaneſs over-flows the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Well, our God is at Work, and he will certainly do great things for <hi>Sion,</hi> and will in his <hi>due time</hi> turn all things to his own Glory, and his Peoples great Good and Benefit: Whether you may live to ſee the <hi>Redemption</hi> of <hi>Sion,</hi> or the <hi>Churches</hi> flouriſh again in this Nation, I cannot tell; But of this I am perſwaded, That you will one Day enjoy a far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtate of Joy and Perfection, without mixture or Chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs; and therefore as a Cordial to your Soul in this earthly Pilgrimage, I have briefly ſet before you a glimpſe of that Glory and Happineſs which the Saints ſhall enjoy in their <hi>Father's Kingdom;</hi> which <hi>Portion</hi> I doubt not but you can claim an Intereſt in, and I hope you will aſſuredly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
<pb facs="tcp:97238:4"/>and poſſeſs it, when the <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Heavens</hi> ſhall be no more. Indeed, Conſidering <hi>your day is</hi> drawing to a <hi>period,</hi> and the great <hi>Troubles, Calamities,</hi> and <hi>Afflictions</hi> which you have ſeen, felt, and undergone; I did judge that I could not preſent unto you a more <hi>ſerious, ſutable,</hi> and <hi>ſeaſonable Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> than this. And Conſidering the <hi>Troubles</hi> of the Day, and the <hi>Rage</hi> of the Adverſary, I have here drawn forth a <hi>Cord of Encouragement,</hi> out of the Scriptures of <hi>Comfort,</hi> as a means to Arm and Fortifie our <hi>Souls</hi> againſt the <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Terrour</hi> of Man; that we may Chearfully &amp; Faithfully <hi>ſtand</hi> to the <hi>Work of the Lord,</hi> notwithſtanding the great <hi>Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions</hi> which we may meet withal from the <hi>Sons of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's that which I <hi>Pen'd</hi> in the time of my <hi>Reſtraint</hi> and <hi>Impriſonment,</hi> when my <hi>Soul</hi> was much exerciſed in the Thoughts of <hi>God's Goodneſs;</hi> And truly, my <hi>Soul</hi> hath ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much ſweetneſs out of this <hi>Heavenly Fountain;</hi> and it's that which hath much Refreſhed, Comforted and born me up in the midſt of <hi>my Sufferings</hi> and <hi>Tryals;</hi> And I hope it will (through the Bleſſing of God) be of the ſame uſe unto your <hi>Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>Lord</hi> by this Diſcourſe ſhould make me (who is the Fruit of your Body) an <hi>Inſtrument</hi> of Joy and Comfort to your <hi>Soul,</hi> in this Day of <hi>trouble</hi> and <hi>difficulty,</hi> I ſhall think my ſelf largely Requited for my Labour in Writing; and ſhall earneſtly deſire that God may have the Glory: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to that end, I ſhall Commend the following <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> to the Bleſſing of God, and your ſerious peruſal; and Reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours by Relation and Affection, to ſerve you as a Son, and a Servant in Chriſt, <hi>EDW. NOBLE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97238:4"/>
            <head>To the Honeſt, and Well-Affected READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF thou art willing to walk in the Paths of Righteouſneſs, that thou mayeſt enjoy Peace and Favour with God; Thou muſt expect to meet with many Troubles, and Afſlictions, Tryals and Temptations in this Earthly Pilgrimage, and many Diſquietments from the hands of men: For here thou art but as a poor Traveller in a ſtrange Countrey, ſubject to be much wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and abuſed by the men of this World; becauſe thou belongeſt to another Countrey, and canſt not Travel with them in the Road of Iniquity; inſomuch that thy Portion (it may be) here may ſeem to be grievous, and thy Burden may ſeem to be heavy: Therefore out of tender Love to thy Soul, I have here Compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Choice Cordial for thee, as a means to Comfort and Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage thee in thy Chriſtian Progreſs, that thou mayeſt not faint, nor be weary in well-doing; for this I can aſſure thee, and that by Experience, That if thou doſt but carry this Heavenly Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al along with thee upon thy Heart, it will make the bittereſt Cup of Affliction ſweet and pleaſant to thee; and the greateſt Burden of Grief and Miſery ſhall be light and eaſie unto thy Soul: And if thou canſt but taſte the ſweetneſs of it, by Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience upon thy Soul, it will make thee think thy ſelf happy,
<pb facs="tcp:97238:5"/>though in the midſt of Miſery, and make thee Rejoyce, though in the midſt of Sorrow, and give thee occaſion to bleſs and praiſe the Name of the Lord, for the worſt of Diſpenſations.</p>
            <p>And leſt thou ſhouldſt at any time be filled and overcome with ſlaviſh Fear, under the Conſideration of thy Earthly Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and be frighted from the Truth by the frowning Rage of thy Enemies; I here preſent thee with an Excellent Antidote againſt the Fear and Terrour of Man, which is known by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, to be of a wonderful ſtrengthning Nature, and if it be kindly received into thy Soul, it will ſufficiently Fortifie and Encourage thee againſt all Oppoſitions whatſoever, and make thee Bold and Couragious for the Cauſe of God, and Crown thee with Victory in Life Eternal.</p>
            <p>So I ſhall commit both thee, and the following <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> to the Bleſſing of God, deſiring thee to Read it Conſiderately, and peruſe it in Love, that ſo it may prove as Food to thy Soul, and Strength to thy Inward Man, to the Praiſe and Glory of him, who hath called thee out of <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> into his marvellous <hi>Light;</hi> which is the Earneſt deſire of his Soul, who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Faithful Friend and Servant, in the Concernments of Jeſus Chriſt, EDWARD NOBLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97238:5"/>
            <head>A Strong Motive to faithful Perſeverance in the <hi>Work</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome;</hi> drawn from that Excellent ſaying of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, recorded in <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.32.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Fear not Little Flock, for it is your Father's good pleaſure to give you the Kingdom.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THeſe Words were ſpoken by no meaner a Perſon, than Him, whom all Chriſtians do freely and readily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to be the <hi>Son of God,</hi> the <hi>Lord of Life,</hi> and <hi>Prince of Peace,</hi> even <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous:</hi> And therefore this in the firſt Place Conſidered, the words themſelves do in a ſpecial manner loudly Call for, and require our more ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſober Conſideration: And the Conſideration thereof ſhould mightily induce us to be ready and willing to receive and imbrace that Doctrine and Counſel which is comprehended in theſe Words, becauſe they proceeded out of the mouth of ſo <hi>gracious, wiſe,</hi> and <hi>wonderful Counſellor;</hi> One, whom his very Enemies could not but Confeſs did ſpeak <hi>as never man ſpake,</hi> Joh. 7.46. And thoſe that were his Followers, and had much Experience concerning him, do faithfully declare, that he had <hi>the Words of eternal life,</hi> Joh. 6.68. Therefore ſurely theſe <hi>Words</hi> muſt needs be of an excellent nature, and of great Concernment unto our Souls, if we do but give dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent heed thereunto; and without doubt, if the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of this <hi>Text,</hi> were but the <hi>Practice</hi> of our <hi>Lives,</hi> we ſhould be able to grapple with, and get victory over all the Temptations, Tryals, and Difficulties of this Life, and our Converſations would migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily conduce to the Glory of God, and to the Eternal well-being of our Souls in the World to come.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:97238:6"/>Well, but let us come a little cloſer to the Words themſelves, and let us ſee what this <hi>bleſſed Counſellor</hi> would have us <hi>learn</hi> from thence; and let us a little examine, what Encouragement he will give us to receive his Doctrine.</p>
            <p>In the Words themſelves, you have Chiefly theſe Three Things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here is an <hi>Exhortation,</hi> or rather a <hi>Dehortation,</hi> to dehort us from ſomething which ought not to be found amongſt us: Or more plainly, here is an Injunction; ſomething enjoyned upon us by way of Duty, which is, <hi>Not to be Afraid;</hi> Contained in cheſe words, [<hi>Fear not.</hi>]</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here are the <hi>Perſons</hi> included, upon whom this Duty is enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and they are the <hi>Diſciples and Church of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in theſe words, [<hi>Little Flock</hi>] <hi>Fear not Little Flock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Here is a great <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Encouragement</hi> laid down to enforce the <hi>Exhortation,</hi> or to ſtir us up to put this neceſſary Duty into Practice; and that's in theſe words, [<hi>For it's your Father's good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to give you the Kingdom.</hi>]</p>
            <p>A Reaſon ſufficient to enforce the Duty, and to Ballance al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions whatſoever.</p>
            <p>It is ſomewhat requiſite that I ſhould ſpeak ſomething concerning this word [<hi>Fear</hi>] before I come to the <hi>Obſervations</hi> of the <hi>Text:</hi> For the better underſtanding of our Saviour concerning this word [<hi>Fear</hi>] if we do but peruſe the fore going part of the Chapter, it may very clearly be diſcerned, that he chiefly intends the Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of theſe two ſorts of <hi>Fear:</hi> Firſt, <hi>Not to be afraid of man, nor of any thing that man can do unto us;</hi> as you may clearly ſee in <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. <hi>And I ſay unto you, My Friends, Be not afraid of them that kill the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and afterwards can do no more:</hi> For the Lord Jeſus Chriſt know right well, that his Diſciples would be exceedingly hated by the World, and that they would meet with implacable Enemies and Adverſaries, which would oppoſe them with great force and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in their journey towards Heaven. Now as a means to Eſtabliſh them in the Truth, and to arm and fortifie them againſt the terrour of theſe implacable Oppoſites, he ſpreads ſeveral Conſiderations before them, from <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. to <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. And at length ſums up all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Exhortation and Encouragement, <hi>Fear not little Flock, for it's your Father's good pleaſure to give you the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, By <hi>Fear</hi> in this <hi>Text,</hi> is intended thus much, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97238:6"/>That we muſt not be afraid of wanting Wordly things relating to the <hi>outward Man,</hi> as Food and Raiment, or any thing that may be convenient and neceſſary for us; for many times the World proves ſuch a ſnare, and ſuch a clogge to Chriſtians, as that it <hi>fetters</hi> and <hi>intangles</hi> them ſo, as they cannot run with patience the <hi>Race</hi> that is ſet before them; and is ready (many times) to pull them back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into <hi>Egypt,</hi> when they are Travelling towards <hi>Canaan;</hi> And to make them, with <hi>Demas,</hi> forſake the <hi>Communion of Saints in the wayes of God,</hi> and to cloſe in with their <hi>Affections to the Tranſitory things of this preſent World.</hi> And many times Chriſtians are very much filled with Fears, and Cares, and Perplexities of Spirit, upon the account of this World, fearing that <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Purity</hi> (being to much oppoſed by the World) will tend too much to <hi>Poverty:</hi> And if they continue and perſevere in that <hi>Path,</hi> they ſhall not be able to find <hi>Temporal Subſiſtance:</hi> And ſo under that Conſideration, they are incident many times to corrupt themſelves, and cloſe in with any thing for Profit and Advantage. Therefore it is the great Care of our Saviour Chriſt, to arm and fortifie them againſt this kind of <hi>Fear</hi> alſo; As you may read at large from <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. to the words of my Text; and there he comes to faſten his Concluding Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and backs it with a very Glorious Encouragement, <hi>Fear not, what ye ſhall do for Food and Raiment;</hi> do but you continue faithful in your Duty towards God, and to be ſure he will continue faithful in his Mercies towards you; and whatever Croſſes and Loſſes you may ſuſtain in this World, yet be of good chear, keep on your way, the time will come when you ſhall largely be made amends for all; when you ſhall receive a hundred fold for every particular lofs: <hi>For it's your Pather's good pleaſure, to give you the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Words being chus <hi>Opened</hi> and <hi>Explained,</hi> I ſhall now come to deduct ſomething from them by way of <hi>Doctrinal Obſervation,</hi> hoping it may (through the Bleſſing of God) be of ſome uſe unto our <hi>Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 1. That <hi>Chriſt's Flock</hi> is but a <hi>little Flock:</hi> A Mean, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, Deſpiſed <hi>little Flock: Little</hi> in compariſon of that great <hi>Multitude</hi> which runs the contrary way. <hi>Mean</hi> and <hi>Contemptible</hi> (in the eyes of the World) in compariſon of the many <hi>Mighty,</hi> and the many <hi>Noble</hi> which belongs to the <hi>Prince of this world.</hi> There are but <hi>few</hi> will come and abide in the Fold of Jeſus, becauſe he will not grant his Flock Liberty to feed upon the fat Paſtures of worldly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97238:7"/>Pleaſures; nor glut themſelves with Sin and Iniquity. There are a great many that will run freely and ſwiftly into the Path of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but there are but a <hi>few</hi> that will run ſo freely into the high-way of Holineſs, and continue in the Paths of Righteouſneſs. Again, there are a great many that will take abundance of Care how they may make themſelves Rich, and how they may grow Great in the World; but there are but a few that will take ſo much Care how they may pleaſe the Lord, or how they may make themſelves Rich in <hi>Faith and good Works,</hi> that ſo they may be <hi>great in the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> And again, There are a great many that follow the <hi>Devi</hi> in the broad-way to <hi>Deſtruction,</hi> but there are but a few that follow <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in the narrow-way to <hi>Salvation;</hi> For <hi>ſtrait is the Gate, and narrow is the Way which leadeth unto Life, and few there be that find it.</hi> And again, <hi>many are Called, but few are Choſen:</hi> So that it ſeems, Chriſt's Flock is but <hi>Little,</hi> and the Children of Election are but <hi>few.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, But what's the Reaſon that Chriſt's Flock is ſo <hi>Little?</hi> And what is the Reaſon that there are ſo <hi>few</hi> runs the narrow-way to <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?</hi> What is the Reaſon or Cauſe (may ſome ſay) why ſo <hi>few</hi> are <hi>ſaved?</hi> I ſhall therefore (through the Aſſiſtance of God) offer to your Conſideration ſome few <hi>Reaſons</hi> or <hi>Grounds,</hi> why I judge ſo <hi>few</hi> belong to the <hi>Flock of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Negatively, <hi>What is not the Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not believe that the <hi>Cauſe</hi> lyes at all in <hi>God,</hi> but altogether in <hi>Man:</hi> It is not becauſe God hath determined, or abſolutely Decreed that no more ſhould be ſaved, as ſome weakly imagine; for God deſires not <hi>the Death of a Sinner,</hi> nor delights in the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of any man;</hi> but rather <hi>Grieves</hi> and <hi>Mourns</hi> over Perſons for their <hi>Iniquities,</hi> and for <hi>deſtroying</hi> themſelves; and is troubled, and ſorrowful <hi>that they will not turn unto him, that they might be ſaved, Pſal.</hi> 81.13. <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.14. compared with <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.27. and 44.4. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.41, 42, &amp;c. So that it's clear from all theſe Scriptures, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with many more which might be given, That it is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath abſolutely Decreed before the Foundation of the World, that no more ſhould be Holy and partake of Salvation; for he is not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that ALL <hi>ſhould come to the knowledge of the Truth, and be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is it, becauſe Chriſt Died for no more, and ſo they want a Saviour; for this is moſt certain, That <hi>Chriſt Died for All,</hi> 1 Tim.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97238:7"/>2.6. Heb. 10.10. for <hi>EVERY Man,</hi> Heb. 2.9. for <hi>the VVorld,</hi> Joh. 3.16. &amp; 4.42. yea, <hi>for the whole VVorld,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Joh, 2.2. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore glad Tydings is to be Preached to every Creature, and all are Commanded to Repent and Believe the Goſpel; ſo that it cannot be, becauſe Chriſt Died for no more; for Chriſt Died as well for thoſe that <hi>deny him,</hi> and for thoſe that <hi>periſh,</hi> as for thoſe that <hi>believe in him,</hi> and <hi>are ſaved,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.1. 1 Cor. 8.11.</p>
            <p>Neither is it becauſe God with-holds the <hi>Means of Salvation</hi> from any man; for God affords ſufficiency of <hi>Means</hi> to all People for their <hi>Salvation,</hi> and puts every one into a Capacity to perform that which he requires at their hands; and God never did, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will Condemn any for that which they <hi>could not do,</hi> but alwayes for that which they <hi>would not do,</hi> Pſal. 81.11. Luk. 13.34. Joh. 5.40. Therefore it is not becauſe. God with-holds the Means of Salvation from any; for he never Requires that from any man to Salvation, which they are not in a Capacity to perform: nor he never Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Impoſſibilities.</p>
            <p>Well, having now ſhewed you <hi>Negatively, VVhat is not the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> I ſhall alſo endeavour to ſhew you <hi>Affirmitively, VVhat is the Reaſon why the Flock of Chriſt is but Little.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Firſt Reaſon,</hi> I judge may be this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe the Reward which Chriſt hath promiſed to his Flock, is in another World, it is not to be found here below on this ſide the Grave, but it is to be enjoyed in another Life. And men generally love preſent things, and are much taken with that which is of a preſent enjoyment: Therefore it is, that moſt men are ſo Careful, and ſo deſirous after the things of this World, becauſe the Benefit and Pleaſures of the things here below, are of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent enjoyment; but the Benefit of Holineſs, and the Reward of God's People is not to be enjoyed in this Life, but in the World to come: Therefore it is that men do ſo little regard the Service of God, becauſe the reward ſeems to be at a great diſtance from them. For I am very much perſwaded, That if the Reward of Godlineſs were but of a preſent Enjoyment, there would be abundance of Godly People, and Chriſt's Flock would be the greateſt Flock in the World: As for Inſtance, Go to a Covetous Worldly-man, and Exhort him to Charity, and deſire him to lay out great part of his Eſtate for the good of the <hi>Poor;</hi> and tell him, That he ſhall be ſure to Receive a Hundred fold for it about a Week or a Fortnight
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97238:8"/>hence; and if he were but really Convinced of the Truth of this, I am perſwaded, he would preſently become a Charitable Perſon, and would eaſily be drawn to part with his Money willingly upon this account: But if you ſhould go to him, and bid him, Sell all that he hath, and give it to the <hi>Poor,</hi> and come and follow Chriſt; and tell him, That he ſhall be ſure to have Treaſure in Heaven, and be eminently Rewarded at the Reſurrection of the Juſt; Oh! how little would this be Regarded by him? Oh! How little would this prevail upon him? Oh! The Reward ſeems to be ſuch a great way off, that he durſt hardly part with his Money up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch terms: Yea, I am perſwaded that he would be ſo far from embracing your Counſel, as that he would rather be troubled and grieved at you, for ſpeaking ſuch Language to him: So that I judge this may be one great <hi>Reaſon,</hi> why the <hi>Flock of Chriſt</hi> is but <hi>Little,</hi> and the <hi>Number of the Elect</hi> but <hi>few.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> Another is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Becauſe the Flock of Chriſt muſt expect to meet with Troubles and Tribulations in their journey towards Heaven: They muſt expect to carry a bitter Cup of Afflictions along with them in their Chriſtian Progreſs; They muſt not expect to ſpend their dayes in Pleaſure and Pride of Life, to promote their own Honour and Reputation in the World: but rather Troubles and Afflictions, Tryals and Temptations, muſt be their daily Portion in this Life: Yea, <hi>All that will live Godly in Chriſt Jeſus, muſt ſuffer Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution:</hi> Therefore this I alſo judge to be another <hi>Reaſon,</hi> why ſo few follow Jeſus Chriſt; becauſe his way is attended with Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and men generally ſeek after their own Pleaſure, Eaſe, and Worldly Advantage; and do not love to Travel in a Suffering-Path, nor walk in a Way that is attended with Straits and Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Now you ſhall find moſt men are very willing to be ſaved, if they could be ſaved upon their own terms, by walking in Pleaſures, and in the vanity of their own minds; but they are not willing to go through Sufferings to Salvation; they are not willing to go to Heaven upon God's terms, nor to follow the Lord Jeſus Chriſt no further than it conſiſts with their own carnal Intereſt &amp; Advantage. Moſt men are willing to <hi>are the Death of the Righteons,</hi> but they are not willing to <hi>live the Life of the Righteous:</hi> They are very willing to receive the <hi>Reward</hi> of the Righteous, but they are not willing to <hi>Run</hi> the <hi>Race</hi> of the Righteous: They are very willing (it may be)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97238:8"/>to <hi>Reign</hi> with Chriſt and wear the <hi>Crown,</hi> but they are not willing to <hi>ſuffer</hi> with Chriſt, and bear the <hi>Croſs:</hi> They are very willing to accept of the Crown of <hi>Glory,</hi> and drink Wine with Chriſt in his <hi>Kingdom:</hi> but they are not willing to accept of the Crown of <hi>Thorns,</hi> and drink Vinegar with Chriſt upon the <hi>Croſs:</hi> Therefore this may be one great Reaſon, why ſo few walk in the way of the Goſpel, becauſe it is attended with <hi>Perſecution;</hi> Therefore ſayes Chriſt, <hi>There are ſome which hear the Word, and receive it with joy, and keep it, and continue in it for a while, ſo long as the world ſmiles upon them; but when Tribulation, or Perſecution ariſeth for the Goſpels ſake, then preſently they fly off, and leave the Goſpel; and by and by are angry and offended with it, for bringing Troubles upon them,</hi> Matth. 13.20, 21. So that it's the Tribulation of the Goſpel, that many times keeps Perſons at a diſtance from the Goſpel, and makes many fall away from it, after Profeſſing of it. And this we can too clearly evidence, and witneſs by experience at this day, That many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons could very willingly follow Jeſus Chriſt in his own way, and walk in the true Order of the Goſpel, according to God's Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but for fear of Trouble and Perſecution, they dare not: For they think, if they ſhould embrace the Truth as it is in Jeſus, and walk in Obedience thereunto, then they may come to loſe the Love (it may be) of Father, or Mother, or ſome other Relations; and all their former Friends will now turn to be their Enemies, and hate them: And thoſe, that uſe to ſpeak well of them formerly, will now Mock and Reproach them, and do them what miſchief they can; and ſo by this means, they may come to expoſe themſelves to a great many ſtraits and difficulties; And therefore under this Conſideration, they ſtand off at a diſtance, and dare not obey the Goſpel, nor come into the Fold of Chriſt. Hence it is, There are many Perſons, that if you ſhould ſay unto them, and ask them; <hi>Are you willing to go to Heaven, and dwell with God to all Eternity in the Kingdom of Glory?</hi> They will be ready to Anſwer, <hi>Yes; Oh! with all my heart; It is the deſire of my Soul to be with God in the Kingdom of Glory.</hi> But if you tell them, That <hi>they muſt go through much Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, and ſuffer much Perſecution, if they will enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done of God:</hi> Then they will be ready to ture their backs of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and ſatisfie themſelves without it, rather than expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſo much trouble about it. So that I judge, this may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother great <hi>Reaſon, why Chriſt's Flock is but little.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:97238:9"/>But <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Another is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. Becauſe there are but a very few great Men that walk in the Truth of the Goſpel; very few eminent Men in Authority will come into the Flock of Jeſus Chriſt; but the Flock of Chriſt generally conſiſts of a Company of Poor, Contemptible Men and Women, who are alwayes accounted as the filth and the off-ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the World; Poor <hi>Fiſher-men,</hi> and <hi>Tent-makers,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Mechanical</hi> Perſons, are generally the honourableſt Perſons in the Flock of Chriſt. But now, moſt People love to follow the Example of Great Men; and that Way which is lightly eſteemed amongſt the Nobility and Gentry, is commonly little Regarded, amongſt the moſt of Men; but that Way and Religion that is honoured, and promoted by them, is very prevalent upon the Affections of moſt People, and much followed and highly eſteemed amongſt the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude: But now the Way of God is very little honoured and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted by great Men; For, <hi>not many Wiſe men after the fleſh, not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Mighty, not many Noble are called; But God hath Choſen the Foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh things of the World, to confound the Wiſe; and the Weak things of the World, to confound the things which are Mighty: And Baſe things of the World, and things which are Deſpiſed, hath God choſen, that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence.</hi> So that it ſeems, the Flock of God conſiſts of a Company of <hi>baſe, fooliſh, weak, deſpiſed, contemptible Creatures,</hi> as to the eyes of the World; and there are but very few Mighty Men of the World will lay aſide their Honour and Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and Travel in ſuch a mean, contemptible path; So that this may be another <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or <hi>Cauſe,</hi> why the Flock of Chriſt is but little; Becauſe moſt People delight to follow the Example of great Men: And there are but a few great Men belong to the Fold of Chriſt. Therefore there is a notable Text for this purpoſe, in <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.47, 48, 49. where the <hi>Jewes</hi> Officers were ſo much taken with Chriſt, as that they could not but ſpeak wonderful well of him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Chief <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Phariſees;</hi> ſaying, <hi>Never man ſpake like this Man:</hi> But when the <hi>Phariſees</hi> perceived, that they began to reliſh the <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Chriſt, They preſently began to put a Block in their way: And cry out, ARE YE ALSO DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CEIVED! Are you ſo mad and fooliſh to be deluded by ſuch a one as He is? Surely we hope you have more Wiſdom in you than to be his Diſciples; For pray Conſider, Have any of the RULERS, or any of the PHARISEES Believed on Him? No, There is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97238:9"/>none follows him but a few Ignorant Curſed People, which knows not the <hi>Law,</hi> therefore you muſt needs be deceived if you follow Him, becauſe you know the RULERS are all Enemies to Him: So that you ſee, the main <hi>Argument</hi> that they made uſe of to diſwade theſe Perſons from following <hi>Jeſus,</hi> is this, The RULERS RUNS the Contrary way.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Fourthly,</hi> and Laſtly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4. Becauſe there is no Honour, Credit, nor Worldly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to be gained, by walking in the Fold of Chriſt: There is very few that will open their mouths to commend and ſpeak well of thoſe that walk faithfully with God in his own way; but rather the contrary; Thoſe that will follow Jeſus Chriſt, in the ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſincerity of the Goſpel; muſt expect to be reproached, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled, defamed, and evil ſpoken of by moſt People; yea, they muſt expect to be made a Reproach to their Neighbours, a Scorn and a Deriſion to them that are round about them, a By-word among the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and a <hi>ſhaking of the Head</hi> among the People: But now moſt men love Honour and Reputation, and delights in the praiſes of Men; and that which is highly eſteemed, and had in admiration by the World, is very pleaſing, and acceptable to moſt People: Therefore this is another great thing that keeps many off, from clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in with the way of the Goſpel, becauſe moſt men love that which is Honourable in the Worlds eye: Therefore ſayes Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.44. <hi>How can ye believe, which receive Honour one of another, and ſeek not that Honour which cometh from God only?</hi> So that while Perſons are ambitious, and deſirous of Worldly Honour, they can never be faithful Followers of Jeſus Chriſt; for that which is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed amongſt men, is abomination in the ſight of God. And again, there is a notable Text for this purpoſe, in <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.42, 43. where there were ſeveral Perſons, among the <hi>Chief Rulers,</hi> believed on Him, but becauſe of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> they did not Confeſs Him, leſt they ſhould loſe their Credit amongſt them, and ſo be caſt out of the <hi>Synagogue.</hi> Why, what was the Matter that they were not faithful to their Conſciences in this Caſe? Why, here's the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; <hi>They loved the Praiſe of men, more than the Praiſe of God.</hi> They did ſee, and perceive, that if they had Confeſſed Him openly, and had declared in good earneſt for Chriſt, then they ſhould preſently have loſt their Credit and Reputation amongſt the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and have expoſed themſelves to <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>reproach;</hi> for they knew, <hi>that the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97238:10"/>way of Chriſt was every where ſpoken againſt,</hi> Acts 28.22. Therefore they would be none of Chriſt's Diſciples, becauſe they were in love with Worldly Honour. Hence it is, that ſo many Rejects the pure Commands and Inſtitutions of Jeſus Chriſt, becauſe they are mean and contemptible in the eyes of the World, and are not trimmed and garniſhed with Rich out-ſides; Therefore it is, that ſo many mock and ſcoff, and jear at that <hi>Heavenly Ordinance</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers Baptiſm;</hi> and would not ſuffer it to have any Being or Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment in the World, becauſe it muſt be done in a poor, mean, and deſpicable manner; I mean as in the account of the world. But if you come to talk with them about that fooliſh foppery, that Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Invention of <hi>Infant Sprinkling,</hi> Oh! that muſt be had in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence by them, and that muſt be highly extol'd and magnified by them, becauſe it is ſo neatly and handſomely done, and gilded with out-ſide gallantry; and of great Repute and very Commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able almoſt in the eyes of every one: For many times there is a brave <hi>Silver Baſon</hi> to hold the Water in, &amp; that makes an honourable ſhow, and pleaſes the Fancy of People exceedingly. And again, many times there is a fine <hi>Soarlet Mantle</hi> to cover the Child, with a <hi>broad Silver Lace</hi> upon it; and that is very pleaſant to behold in a Carnal eye: And ſeveral other <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> which are very decent and commendable in the account of the World; and therefore it is, that this vain and Scripture-leſs Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice is ſo acceptable to moſt People. So that I judge, this may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be another great <hi>Reaſon</hi> why Chriſt hath ſo few Diſciples, becauſe there is no worldly Honour to be found in the way of Chriſt; and moſt men love not Shame and Reproach.</p>
            <p>So I ſhall leave theſe few Hints to your ſerious Conſideration, and Conclude this ſhort <hi>Point</hi> with a brief <hi>Word of Caution,</hi> and ſo proceed to a <hi>Second Obſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then, ſeeing it is ſo, that the Flock of Chriſt is but Little, let us take heed that we do not run aſtray from Chriſt, and ſo make it leſſer: Let us take heed that we do not wander out of the Fold of Chriſt, and run after other Shepherds. Let us take heed that we do not leave the voice of Chriſt, and hearken to the voice of Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; but ſeeing we have given up our Names to Jeſus Chriſt, let us endeavour (through the ſtrength of the Lord) to follow Him chearfully and willingly in all his Temptations; and let us remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Lord is our Shepherd, therefore we ſhall want nothing that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97238:10"/>is good and convenient for us; and then the Lord will take ſpecial care of us to deliver us out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and to preſerve us in the <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs,</hi> till we come to that eternal Reſt, which yet remains for the People of God: And though we may be ſcattered in a cloudy and dark Day, yet the Lord will in a ſhort time Return to his Flock and ſeek them out, and gather them together, and carry them in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and feed them upon the Mountains of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and they ſhall no more be a Prey to the <hi>Heathen,</hi> neither ſhall the Beaſts of the Land Devour them; but the Lord their God ſhall be with them, and they ſhall Dwell ſafely, and none ſhall make them afraid.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall Proceed now to a <hi>Second Obſervation</hi> from the Text, which is this;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> 2. That <hi>the Saints and Servants of God, ſhould not be afraid of the worſt that man can do unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Third</hi> and <hi>Laſt Obſervation</hi> from the Text, is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 3. That <hi>it is the good pleaſure of Almighty God, to provide and prepare a Kingdom for his People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not ſpeak any thing further concerning that Covetous kind of <hi>Fear,</hi> which I laſt ſpoke of in the <hi>Explanation;</hi> But I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to Apply my ſelf to the Two laſt <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> they being Chiefly upon my Heart to Proſecute at this time, from this Text; Therefore I ſhall return to the <hi>Second Obſervation,</hi> which was this;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 2. That <hi>the Saints and People of God ſhould not be afraid of the worſt that man can do unto them.</hi> They ſhould not be daunted, nor terrified at the worſt Newes that they can hear out of the mouths of men; nor at the worſt Puniſhment that they can receive from the hands of men: but they ſhould ſtill be bold, and couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſtrong and valiant for the Cauſe of God, and for the Intereſt of Jeſus, though it may be attended with never ſo many Troubles and Oppoſitions: Yea, though ſtripes and buffettings ſhould daily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend us (if it be upon the account of God) we ſhould be ſo far from being afraid, as that we ſhould rather Rejoyce, that we are counted worthy to ſuffer any thing for the Name of Jeſus. Poſſibly the men of the World may be filled with madneſs againſt us, and put us in Priſons, by Hundreds and Thouſands, and violently threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten us with Halter and Gibbet: Well, be it ſo; we ſhould notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, be Reſolute in the ſtrength of the Lord, and not be afraid nor diſcouraged at <hi>Rabſhekah's</hi> Railing, nor yet at <hi>Nebuchadnezzar's</hi> Fury. See a notable Text to bind this Duty, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2.6. <hi>And thou
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97238:11"/>Son of Man, be not afraid of them, neither be afraid of their words:</hi> As much as if he ſhould ſay, Though they may magnifie themſelves againſt thee with high and lofty Language, and inſult over thee with great and ſwelling words; yet fear them not, neither let their words terrifie thee. Again further, ſayes the Text, <hi>Though Briars and Thornes be with thee, and thou doſt dwell among Scorpions:</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, Though they ſhould be rough as Thornes, and ſharp as Briars againſt thee, &amp; put forth their perſecuting hands againſt thee, to ſcratch and tear thee in pieces (as it were) with their Stocks and Whipping-Poſts; and though they ſhould <hi>Hiſs</hi> and <hi>Spit</hi> their <hi>venome</hi> at thee, like ſo many <hi>Scorpions,</hi> and threaten thee with Death; yet be not afraid, for all this; neither be daunted nor diſmaid at their proud looks, though they be a Rebellious Houſe. Oh! that Profeſſours at this day were but thus valiant for God, and thus bold for the Cauſe of Jeſus Chriſt. But Oh! how doth the Contrary appear amongſt Profeſſors at this Day, to the great diſhonour of God, and to the great grief of thoſe who are truly ſincere? Oh! how baſe and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly doth many eminent Profeſſors prove in this day of Adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? How are they ready to caſt off all their Religion, and to cloſe in with the Worſhippers of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and all out of a <hi>ſlaviſh fear</hi> of their perſecuting Enemies? Well, but the Lord hath a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie againſt ſuch Back-ſliding Profeſſours, and they ſhall not eſcape the hands of his wrath; for thoſe that forgets the Name of the Lord in ſuch a Day as this, and ſtretches out their Hands to a ſtrange god, the Lord will ſurely ſearch them out, <hi>for he knoweth the ſecrets of the heart,</hi> Pſal. 44.20, 21.</p>
            <p>But we will ſee what the Scripture ſaith in another place, for the Proof of this <hi>Propoſition,</hi> Iſa. 51.7. <hi>Hearken unto me ye that know Righteouſneſs</hi> (ſayes the Text) <hi>the People, in whoſe heart is my Law:</hi> Well, what's the matter that the Spirit of God calls ſo loudly for our Attention? What is it that the Lord doth ſo earneſtly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to preſs upon his People? See the following words, <hi>Fear ye not the Reproach of men, neither be afraid of their Revilings:</hi> Though the Wicked may Reproach and Revile you, and make you as the off-ſcouring of the World, yet that muſt not be regarded by you; that muſt be no excuſe for you to be weary in well-doing, but you muſt ſtill go on in the Work of the Lord, and follow after Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; and fear not, but God will make you more than Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97238:11"/>Thus much ſhall ſuffice for the Proof of this 2d. <hi>Propoſition:</hi> I ſhall now come to give you ſome <hi>Reaſons,</hi> or <hi>Encouragements,</hi> againſt the <hi>fear of Man,</hi> and ſhew you (in ſome meaſure) <hi>why the Saints &amp; Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God need not be afraid of the worſt that man can do unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe the Lord himſelf will be continually with them in all their Troubles, to ſupport and comfort them: He will come and viſite them (if they continue faithful to him) with his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting Preſence, and be a Companion with them in all their Troubles: He will never leave, nor forſake his People in the worſt Condition that may befal them; Therefore great Reaſon why we ſhould not <hi>fear what Man can do unto us:</hi> You ſhall find by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting the Scriptures, That the People of God in old time, did make this Conſideration a grand Reaſon, or Encouragement againſt the fear of Man in the worſt of Troubles. And indeed, this is a very glorious Encouragement for poor Souls to ſtay themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in time of Trouble, to Conſider, That the Lord is with them in all their Troubles, and takes ſpecial notice of all their Afflictions, and he is ready at any time to put under his everlaſting Arm to bear up their Souls, and ſupport them under the worſt of Tryals, and in his due time to deliver them out of all their Afflictions. Well, but wee'l ſee what the Scripture ſayes concerning this matter: See firſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4. <hi>Yea</hi> (ſayes the Pſalmiſt) <hi>though I walk through the valley of the ſhadow of Death, yet will I fear no evil:</hi> (Mark) how bold and reſolute the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> is in the midſt of ſtrange Difficulties: As much as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Although I ſhould walk in a dangerous val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, and mine Enemies at the top of the Hill, ready to overwhelm me with deſtruction; and though Death ſhould purſue me, and be as near to me as my ſhadow, yet will I fear no evil.</hi> Why <hi>David,</hi> what's the matter, that thou art ſo exceedingly tranſported above the <hi>fear of evil?</hi> Certainly, thou haſt ſome Reaſon for it, thou could'ſt never be ſo full of Courage in ſuch eminent Danger as thou ſpeakeſt of, if thou hadſt not ſomething more than ordinary to Support thy Spirit. See the Reaſon therefore in the following words, <hi>THE LORD IS WITH ME.</hi> There's the buſineſs; there's that which is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to fortify my Soul againſt all fear whatſoever: <hi>Thy ROD and thy STAFF, they Comfort me:</hi> As much as if he ſhould ſay, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thy <hi>Rod</hi> doth a little <hi>Correct me,</hi> yet thy <hi>Staff</hi> doth exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Support me,</hi> and thy <hi>PRESENCE</hi> doth very much <hi>Refreſh me;</hi> and betwixt them all, I am mightily filled with Comfort and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97238:12"/>Thus the Saints, and People of God, ſhould Plead their Intereſt in him, in a day of Adverſity, and he will make all things Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and pleaſant unto their Souls, and nothing ſhall be able to make them afraid. See alſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.1, 2, 3. <hi>God is our Refuge and Strength, a very preſent help in time of Trouble:</hi> Well, what then? What uſe doth the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> make of this? Why, <hi>therefore will we not fear, though the Earth ſhould be removed, and though the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains be carried into the midſt of the Sea, though the Waters thereof roar and be troubled, and though the Mountains ſhake with the ſwelling thereof.</hi> Here's an admirable Spirit filled with Confidence, and godly Reſolution in the ſtrength of the Lord, Challenging (as it were) the greateſt Terrours on Earth, to ſhew themſelves in their greateſt Rage and Fury; yet they ſhall not ſo much as diminiſh his Courage, nor make him afraid: And the Reaſon of all is this, <hi>GOD IS OUR REFUGE AND STRENGTH:</hi> So that it ſeems, the Conſideration of God's ſupporting Preſence, is, or ought to be one great <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Encouragement</hi> to bear up our Souls in the worſt of Troubles: Therefore when troubles do attend us, and when our Enemies are moſt implacable againſt us, and talk of Stoning of us, and Baniſhing of us, and putting of us to Death, and the like; let us with <hi>David,</hi> encourage our ſelves in the Lord our God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.6. And let us conſider, <hi>the Lord is with us, and he is a preſent Help in time of Trouble; and if God be for us, who can be againſt us?</hi> Therefore (ſaith God) <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.10. <hi>Fear thou not, for I am with thee; be not diſmaid, for I am thy God; I will ſtrengthen thee, yea, I will help thee; yea, I will uphold thee with the right hand of my Righteouſneſs:</hi> As much as if God ſhould ſay, Although all the World ſhould be againſt thee, yet fear thou not, keep cloſe to me, and I will be with thee; and although thou haſt never ſo many E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies and Adverſaries to oppoſe thee, yet be not diſmaid, <hi>for I am thy God, and I will ſtrengthen thee;</hi> And though they ſet themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, to wrong and oppreſs thee, yet be of good chear, I will help thee, and take thy part againſt them: And though they think to Conquer thy Spirit, and ſubdue the ſtrength of thy Inward-man, by Impriſoning and Puniſhing of thee; yet be not troubled at that, do but put thy Truſt in me, and depend upon me, and I will up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thee with the right hand of my Righteouſneſs; Therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord is ſo much engaged for the good of his People, let's not <hi>fear what man can do unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:97238:12"/>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Why <hi>we ſhould not fear man:</hi> Becauſe the Lord himſelf will engage and fight againſt the Enemies of his People, and bring them to a reckoning for all their Malice and Cruelty towards them, though they may tyrannize and inſult over God's Heritage for a time, and magnifie themſelves againſt the Lord and his Jewels; yet the time will come, when the Lord himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> appear againſt them in Wrath and Judgement, and daſh them in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ces like a Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter's Veſſel, for their Rage and Cruelty againſt his People; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this may be another <hi>Reaſon</hi> to arm us againſt the <hi>fear of Man,</hi> becauſe the Lord hath engaged to deal with our Adverſaries in Judgement, and Recompence Fury upon our Enemies for all their Tyranny towards us, and will aſſuredly work Deliverance and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for his People from all their Troubles. See that notable Text, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.25, 26. <hi>But thus ſaith the Lord, Even the Captives of the Mighty ſhall be taken away, and the Prey of the Terrible ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered; for I will contend with them that contendeth with thee, and I will ſave thy Children; and I will feed them that oppreſs thee, with their own fleſh, and they ſhall be drunken with their own blond, as with ſwoet Wine; and all fleſh ſhall know that I the Lord am thy Saviour, and the Mighty One of</hi> Jacob <hi>thy Redeemer:</hi> Thus the Lord will one Day deal with the enemies of his People, when they have filled up the Meaſure of their Iniquity, then they ſhall aſſuredly Drink the dreggs of the Cup of God's Fury; and when they are at the higheſt, raging, and roaring, and ſwelling in Malice like the Sea, againſt the People of the Lord, then is their deſtruction the neareſt, and then is <hi>Sions</hi> Deliverance near at hand. Read and Conſider well that Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 17.12, 13, 14. compared with <hi>Chap.</hi> 59.15. to the latter end; <hi>Wo to the multitude of many People, which make a noiſe like the noiſe of the Seas, and like the ruſhing of many Waters; the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall Ruſh, like the Ruſhings of mighty Waters; But GOD SHALL REBUKE them: And they ſhall flee, and be chaſed as the Chaff of the Mountains before the wind, and as Thiſtle-down before a Whirle-wind: Behold, this is the Portion of them that ſpoil us, and the Lot of them that Rob us, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! Little doth our Enemies Conſider, what miſchief they are a heaping upon their own heads, when they drive on ſo furiouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the People of God, and Perſecute the innocent Lambs of Jeſus Chriſt without a Cauſe: What account do you think they can give to the Lord, when he ſhall call them to a Reckoning for theſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97238:13"/>things? And how will they be able to ſtand before the Lord, when he ſhall bring them to a Tryal, for dragging his People out of their Houſes from their Callings, and caſting them into Priſons and Dungeons, and keeping of them there by Hundreds and Thouſands for nothing but becauſe they are Godly, and becauſe they love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and dare not ſin againſt the Lord? Surely the Hand of the Lord will one Day take hold of Judgement for theſe things, and he will aſſuredly render Vengeance to his Enemies, and reward them that hate him, for the <hi>Arrows</hi> of the Lord are ordained againſt the <hi>Perſecutors, Deut.</hi> 32.41, 42. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.13. Therefore, though the enemies of God may now flouriſh and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper for a while, and lye upon Beds of Ivory, and ſtretch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon their Couches, and eat the Lambs out of the Flock, and the Calves out of the Stall, and drink Wine in Bowels, and annoint themſelves with the chief Ointments; yet when the Lord comes to Plead with the Nations for the Controverſie of <hi>Sion;</hi> Then they will be ready to run and hide themſelves in the Dens, and in the Rocks of the Mountains, and call to the Mountains and Rocks to fall on them, and hide them from the face of him that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb.</p>
            <p>Therefore under this Conſideration, let's not faint, nor be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged in our Progreſs towards Heaven; for if the Lord be on our ſide, we need <hi>not fear what Man can do unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. Becauſe our greateſt, and our worſt Adverſaries (I mean our Perſecutors) are but Men that ſhall die, poor, vile, ſinful, mortal men, whoſe Breath is in their noſtrils, whoſe Lives are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, and whoſe greateſt glory is but periſhing vanity, and when they are at their greateſt ſtrength, and in their greateſt Pride; The Lord can but put forth his hand and touch them, and lo they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as nothing; and the Lord can but put forth his voice, and call for their Breath, and lo they become but duſt, and meat for Worms; Therefore great Reaſon why we ſhould not be afraid of their greateſt Terrour: For alas, they may threaten great things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the People of God; yea, and be ready to Swear (it may be) that ſuch and ſuch things ſhall be done unto them the next Week, or the next Month, when (it may be) the next day they themſelves are ſummoned to their Graves, and ſo never live to ſee their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Deſignes accompliſhed. Therefore ſee how the Scripture Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves Perſons under this Conſideration, for being afraid of man:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97238:13"/>
               <hi>Iſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 51.12, 13. <hi>Who art thou, that thou ſhouldſt be afraid of man, that ſhall DYE, and of the Son of man which ſhall be made as GRASSE; And forgetteſt the Lord thy Maker, that hath ſtretched forth the Heavens, and laid the Foundations of the Earth; and haſt feared continually every day, becauſe of the fury of the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſour, as if he were ready to deſtroy: and where is the fury of the Oppreſſour?</hi> So that it is below the Spirit of a Saint, to be afraid of any periſhing Creature: it is a ſhame for a Living Saint, to be afraid of a Dying Sinner; it is a great diſhonour to God, for Saints to be afraid of a mortal man, and forget the fear of the living God; it's a ſhame for a Saint, whoſe ſtrength is in the Lord, to be afraid of a man whoſe greateſt ſtrength is weakneſs; it's a ſhame for a Saint, whoſe hope and Confidence is in the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> to be afraid of a man, whoſe Expectation ſhall periſh; it's a horrid thing that Saints ſhould be more afraid to ſerve the <hi>Lord,</hi> then wicked men are to ſerve the <hi>Devil:</hi> Therefore let us hold faſt the Profeſſion of our Faith without wave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and never <hi>fear what man can do unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea.</hi> 4. Becauſe though we may be troubled, and diſturbed on every ſide by man, yet we have Peace and Favour with God; and though men may account us as the filth and the off-ſcouring of the World, yet the Lord doth eſteem us as his Jewels, and his peculiar Treaſure; And this may be ſufficient to bear up our Souls in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of troubles, to conſider, That though the World may hate us with cruel hatred, yet the Lord loveth the Righteous, and taketh pleaſure in his People; and though the World may be our Enemy, and frown upon us, yet the Lord is our Friend, and will ſmile upon us, with the Light of his Countenance, and refreſh our Souls with the choice manifeſtations of his Spirit, and preſence; and though in the World we may have Tribulation and Sorrow, yet in God we may have Peace and Comfort, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſee where our Saviour Chriſt makes this a great Reaſon againſt Fear, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.27. where he ſpeaks thus; <hi>Peace I leave with you, my Peace I give unto you, not as the world giveth, give I unto you;</hi> for alas the world many times giveth Peace, and preſently takes it away again; it may give Peace and reſt a little to Day, and (it may be) Sorrow and Trouble to Morrow; But now ſayes Chriſt, I give not Peace after this manner; <hi>But my Peace ILEAVE with you,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:97238:14"/>that is, it ſhall continue and Tarry with you, and none ſhall be able to take it from you; Well what then? ſuppoſe it be ſo why, let not your hearts be Troubled, neither let them be afraid for though your Enemies may Rob and Deprive you of your outward Comforts, and outward Enjoyments, yet they ſhall never be able to eaſt you out of my Favour, nor Deprive you of that inward Comfort and Spiritual Refreſhment, that I will give unto you, and leave with you; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be not afraid of their Terrour, neither let your hearts be Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. And ſo, likewiſe ſee the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, 3. <hi>Therefore being Juſtified by Faith, we have Peace with God, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord;</hi> So that now, we do not onely Rejoyce in the hope of Glory; But, we alſo <hi>Rejoyce and Glory in all our Tribulations, and are filled with Comfort in all our afflictions,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.4. Therefore let us en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to keep in the Love and Favour of God, and then we need not <hi>fear what man can do unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea.</hi> 5. Becauſe all our Sufferings, (which are for Righteouſneſs ſake) work together for our good and great advantage, and will add to our future Glory and happineſs; there is no miſery that can befall us, upon the account of Godlineſs, but it will prove an addition to to our Eternal Happineſs; Every ſtep we trace in ſorrow, will be to the increaſe of our Eternal Joy. Therefore this may be another great Reaſon, why we ſhould not fear the worſt that man can do unto us; for alas, whatever they do unto us they cannot hurt us, if we keep cloſe to God, they can do us no Injury at all; Nay, the more they Perſecute us (if it be for Chriſt) the more it will conduce to our Good and Benefit. Oh what a glorious Encouragement is this for poor Perſecuted Saints, to hold out in a Day of Tryal, and to bear up their Souls with Joy in the midſt of Troubles! How is it poſſible (me thinks) for Souls to be dejected and caſt down under Afflictions, and to turn their backs of God in a day of Adverſity, if they did but ſeriouſly conſider of theſe things. For <hi>who is, he that can harm you, if you be followers of that which is Good,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. See alſo that notable place, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16, 17. where the Apoſtles themſelves made this conſideration a great ſupport to their Souls under all their Troubles: <hi>For which Cauſe,</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>we faint not, but though our outward man periſh, yet our inward man is renewed Day by Day; For our light affliction which is but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and Eternal weight of Glory.</hi> So that you may ſee, All our Temporal afflictions, are but ſo many
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97238:14"/>Soul Advantages, and all our Earthly L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, will be made up to us in Heavenly Treaſure, and all our Croſſes will but make our Crown of Glory the greater; therefore under this Conſideration, Let's <hi>go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with Boldneſs in the way of the Lord, and never fear what Man can do unto us,</hi> Gen. 50.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea.</hi> 6. Becauſe, (if we continue Faithful to God) he will give us a Crown of Life, and a Kingdom of Glory; he will Eminently reward us with an unmoveable Kingdom, and with an Incorruptible Inheritance which fadeth not away: Though we may for a time be attended with a great many Troubles and Difficulties, and may be expoſed to many outward Calamities in this Life, yet the time will come, when we ſhall be wholly Freed from all Sorrow and Trouble of what Nature ſoever, and ſhall be filled with unſpeakable Joy in the Kingdom of Glory to all Eternity; And this is that which may exceedingly Support us under Sufferings, and Arm us againſt the Fear of Man, to conſider, that we who are now Deſpiſed, and Trampled under Foot, and made as the off-ſcouring of the World, ſhall one Day be Honoured, and Dignified with a Crown of Glory, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted with Jeſus Chriſt in his Throne and Kingdom; Therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. Compared with Rom. 8.17. <hi>If we ſuffer with him, we ſhall alſo Reign with him, and be Partners together with him in Glory.</hi> Oh this may mightily encourage us to preſevere with Boldneſs in the Work of the Lord, and exceedingly Fortifie us againſt the Fear of Man, and Ballance all Oppoſitions whatſoever; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſhall find, our Saviour Chriſt makes this a grand Reaſon or Encouragement againſt Fear, in the words of my Text, Luke 12.32. <hi>Fear not, little Flock; though you are but Little, Mean, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible in the Eyes of the World, yet Fear not, be not afraid of them which kill the Body, and Endeavour like Wolves to deſtroy you;</hi> Why what's the matter, that we muſt ſo little regard the Terrour of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries? Why here's the Buſineſs; <hi>For its your FATHERS good PLEASURE to give you the KINGDOM;</hi> Therefore ſeeing we have ſuch a glorious Portion to receive from the hands of our Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let's never be afraid of our Earthly Enemy See alſo that notable Text, Rev. 2.10. <hi>Fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt Suffer; Behold the Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into Priſon, that ye may be Tryed, and ye ſhall have Tribulation certain Dayes; yet notwithſtanding, Fear none of theſe things.</hi> Though the Devil and his Inſtruments may prevail
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97238:15"/>againſt thee for a ſeaſon, to Impriſon and Perſecute thee; yet be not afraid, but be <hi>thou faithful unto death,</hi> and for thy Encouragement herein, I will aſſure thee thou ſhalt loſe nothing by it, for thou ſhalt certainly <hi>receive a Crown of Life,</hi> and be exalted with me in my <hi>Throne</hi> and <hi>Kingdom:</hi> Therefore, let us have <hi>respect unto this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of Reward,</hi> and chuſe rather <hi>to ſuffer Afflictions with the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of Sin for a ſeaſon.</hi> And let's not be dejected, nor caſt down, nor be afraid of our Adverſaries, when they reproach and impriſon us, and deprive us from our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and Relations, and threaten us with Ruin and Deſolation, as to our outward man; but let us be content and chearful, if it be for Chriſt, let them do their worſt, we ſhall have ſatisfaction enough at the day of Account, when God makes up his <hi>Jewels,</hi> and calls his People to their <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Kingdom:</hi> For what man is there, that would not be content and willing to loſe a Penny, or two Pence, if he were ſure to gain a Thouſand Pounds by it? How much more ſhould we be content and willing to loſe any thing of this World for Chriſt, ſo long as we are ſure we ſhall receive ſuch an Eternal, and unſpeakable Portion in the World to come? <hi>For every one that hath forſaken Houſes, or Brethren, or Siſters, or Pather, or Mother, or Wife, or Children, or Lands for Chriſt's ſake, ſhall receive an hundred fold at the Reſurrection of the Juſt, and in the World to come, Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life,</hi> Mat. 19.29. Therefore ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> Chap. 1.12. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that endureth Temptation, for when he is tryed, he ſhall receive a Crown of Life; which the Lord hath promiſed to thoſe that love him:</hi> Wherefore we receiving a <hi>Kingdom, which cannot be moved, Let us abound in the Work and Service of the Lord, and never fear what man can do unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall now come to make a little <hi>Uſe,</hi> or <hi>Application</hi> of this <hi>Point,</hi> and ſo proceed to a third and laſt <hi>Obſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. Well then, is it ſo, <hi>That the Saints and People of God, ought not to be Afraid of the worſt that Man can do unto them?</hi> Then in the firſt place, by way of <hi>Caution,</hi> Let us take heed of being fearful and faint-hearted in the <hi>VVork</hi> and <hi>Cauſe</hi> of God: Let's take heed of neglecting any part of our Duty towards God, out of a ſlaviſh Fear towards the Threatnings of Man; Oh! let us take heed now, that we do not Diſhonour the Lord, and wrong our own Souls, by a baſe, fearful, unbelieving ſpirit, in this Day of <hi>Jacob's</hi> Troubles; when the Lord ſhall call us forth, to bear a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> for his <hi>Name</hi> and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97238:15"/>
               <hi>Cauſe,</hi> which are ſo much Blaſphemed and Trampled under foot, as it is at this day: Let us take heed, that the Devil do not catch us in the ſnare of ſlaviſh Fear, and ſo hinder us, and ſtop us in our Proceedings for God, and in our Reſolutions for Chriſt; and cauſe us to Comply with the Enemies of Godlineſs, and joyn iſſue with the Workers of Iniquity; to the great Diſhonour of God, and to the encouraging and gladning the hearts of our Enemies; and to the wounding and ſadning the Souls of thoſe that are truly faithful: I ſay, let us take heed of theſe things, leſt we ſhamefully turn our backs of God in a day of <hi>Adverſity,</hi> out of a ſlaviſh Fear, of Suffering from the hands of Men. Oh! we might here lament the Apoſtacy of abundance of Profeſſors, ſince the Lord hath been pleaſed to turn his hand of <hi>Tryall</hi> upon them: Oh! how have many Profeſſors at this day, <hi>made ſhipwrack of Faith and a good Conſcience,</hi> and highly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the purity of the Goſpel, and baſely turned their backs of the Truth, as it is in Jeſus; and all out of a ſlaviſh Fear of the Frowns and Diſpleaſure of Man? Oh! how have many Profeſſors at this day, who have formerly born a glorious <hi>Teſtimony</hi> for God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Antichriſt, yet now hath filthily defiled their hands with Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and corrupted their hearts with Covetouſneſs, and lifted up their Souls to Vanity, and Sworn Deceitfully to <hi>Babylon;</hi> and all to avoyd <hi>Sufferings,</hi> and to advance their own Intereſt and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in the World: Therefore I ſay again, Let us take heed to our ſelves, leſt there ſhould creep into any of us <hi>an evil heart of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, in departing from the living God; for we ſhall be made partakers with Chriſt, if we hold faſt the beginning of our Confidence ſtedfaſt unto the end.</hi> Therefore, whatever we may Suffer or undergo for God, let us take heed of declining the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of God, and forſaking his Intereſt: for it is written, <hi>The juſt ſhall live by Faith; but if any man draw back, my Soul ſhall have no pleaſure in him.</hi> And again, the <hi>Backſlider in heart, ſhall be filled with his own ways,</hi> Heb. 10.38. Prov. 14.14.</p>
            <p>Therefore when we meet with oppoſitions in the Wayes of God, Let's not be afraid nor terrified at them; if they ſhall threaten us with a <hi>Priſon</hi> for our Integrity, let's not be afraid of a <hi>Priſon,</hi> but chearfully and willingly forſake all, and embrace a <hi>Priſon,</hi> rather than forſake our Intereſt in God, to embrace this preſent world: If they ſhall threaten us with <hi>Baniſhment,</hi> for our Love to the <hi>Truth;</hi> Let not the fear of <hi>Baniſhment,</hi> cauſe us to turn our backs upon the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97238:16"/>
               <hi>Truth,</hi> and be afraid to own it; knowing, that neither <hi>Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> nor <hi>Baniſhment,</hi> can deprive us of the preſence of God, nor caſt us out of the favour of him, in whoſe <hi>preſence is fulneſs of joy, and at whoſe right hand, are pleaſures for evermore:</hi> But if we out of a ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Fear, neglect our Duty towards God, and turn from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of the Lord; then we ſhall loſe the favour of God, and draw the Judgments of the Lord upon us, and ſplit our Souls againſt the Rock of his Diſpleaſure; Therefore ſaith God to <hi>Jeremiah, Jer.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Gird up thy loyns and ariſe, and ſpeak unto them, all that I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand thee; be not diſmayed at their faces, leſt I confound thee before them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a notable place in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44. which is worthy of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and alſo of our Imitation and Practice; it is a glorious Account of the <hi>Churches Faithfulneſs</hi> in an <hi>evil Day,</hi> and in a <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted State, Pſal.</hi> 44.9. and ſo forward: <hi>Thou haſt caſt off, and put us to ſhame; Thou haſt given us like Sheep appointed for meat, and haſt ſcattered us among the Heathen: Thou makeſt us a Reproach to our Neighbours, a Scorn and a Deriſion to them that are round about us: Thou makeſt us a By-word among the Heathen, a ſhaking of the Head among the People.</hi> Here's a miſerable State indeed, for a People to undergo, full of Troubles and Sorrow, and full of Contempt and Reproach, and full of Diſtreſs and Miſery: Well, but did they not turn back in ſuch a day as this? Is it poſſible for them to hold out, in the midſt of ſo many Difficulties? Did they not forſake the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of God, and decline his Intereſt, in ſuch a <hi>Perſecuted State</hi> as this? Noe, not at all: See <hi>verſ.</hi> 17, 18. <hi>All this is come upon us, yet we have not forgotten thee; neither have we dealt falſely with thy Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; Our heart is not turned back, neither have our ſteps declined from thy way.</hi> Therefore now let us conſider, and make this Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it unto our Souls; whatever <hi>Sufferings</hi> we may meet withal, upon the Account of Godlineſs; Let us not fear, let us not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed, let us not value the worſt that Man can do unto us.</p>
            <p>Thus much in the firſt place, by way of <hi>Caution;</hi> But <hi>Secondly,</hi> by way of <hi>Exhortation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. Is it ſo, <hi>That the Saints and People of God, ſhould not be A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of the worſt that Man can do unto them?</hi> Why then, let us not only be <hi>Cautioned from Fear,</hi> but let us be <hi>Exhorted to Courage;</hi> Let us no only be Dehorted from the Vice of <hi>Fear;</hi> but let us alſo be Exhorted to the contrary <hi>Vertue;</hi> Let us not only be found paſſive
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97238:16"/>in that which is not our Duty; but let us alſo be found active in that which is our Duty; that ſo we may be compleat in the Will of God, and glorifie him in the whole courſe of our Lives and Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Hence then, let us be Exhorted to be Bold and Couragious, ſtrong and valiant for the <hi>Cauſe of God,</hi> and the Intereſt of Jeſus Chriſt; though we meet with never ſo many Diſſiculties and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions in this World: Let us count nothing too dear to loſe for Chriſt, feeing he hath counted nothing too dear to loſe for us: If the Lord ſhall call for loſs of <hi>Liberty</hi> at our hands, in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> let us chearfully give up our <hi>Liberties</hi> to the Lord, and embrace a <hi>Priſon:</hi> If the Lord ſhall call for the leaving of Friends and Relations, and take us from our Callings, and call for the loſs of Goods and Eſtate; let us freely and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give up all for God, and be content without them, and ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e as bold as Lyons in our Teſtimony for Chriſt; knowing that the time will come, when we ſhall have a hundred fold returned into our boſomes; and the time will come, when we ſhall ſerve God in his holy Temple, and he that fitteth on the Throne ſhall dwell amongſt us, and we ſhall <hi>hunger no more,</hi> neither ſhall we <hi>thirſt any more;</hi> for the <hi>Lamb which is in the midſt of the Throne ſhall feed us,</hi> and ſhall <hi>lead us into fountains of living Water:</hi> Therefore I ſay, let us go on with much boldneſs in the Work of the Lord, and let us make it appear to the World, that we are reſolved (through the ſtrength of the Lord) to <hi>obey God rather than man;</hi> yet, let us manifeſt ſo much Courage in our Chriſtian Warfare, as to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to become any thing, yea, to become nothing, ſo the Glory of God may be promoted and advanced by us: Therefore in this Caſe, let us take the Counſel of <hi>David</hi> to his Son <hi>Solomon,</hi> when the Lord requires any thing at our hands to be done for the honour of his Name; Let us be <hi>STRONG and of good COURAGE,</hi> and do it; <hi>Fear not, nor be diſmayed, for the Lord God, even our God, will be with us; he will not fail us, nor forſake us, till we have finiſhed all our work for the Service of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.20.</p>
            <p>Oh! we ſhould very much glorifie God, and adorn the Profeſſion of the Goſpel, if we are but valiant for the Truth upon the Earth, and take the Tribulations of the Goſpel chearfully and joyfully; yea, we ſhall make our very Enemies admire at us, if we have but a right ſpirit upon this account: when they ſhall ſee and take notice, how we are troubled on every ſide, and how we are Perſecuted and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97238:17"/>Afflicted, and trampled under foot, and yet we are chearful, and full of Courage, and not at all daunted nor terrified at it: They muſt needs think there is more than ordinary in our Profeſſion, and ſo by that means God is exceedingly glorified, and his Truth admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his Enemies; though poſſibly they may ſtill obſtinately and willingly oppoſe it, yet notwithſtanding, they ſhall by this means be left without excuſe; and the power of the Truth ſhall witneſs againſt them, to the praiſe and glory of God, and to the peace and comfort of our own Souls: Therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.14 <hi>If ye be reproached for the Name of Chriſt, happy are ye; for the Spirit of Glory reſteth upon you: On their part he is evil ſpoken of, but on your part he is glorified.</hi> There is alſo a notable paſſage of our Saviour Chriſt concerning <hi>Peter,</hi> John 21.18, 19. <hi>Verily, verily,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt unto <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>when thou waſt young, thou girdeſt thy ſelf, and walkeſt whither thou wouldſt; but when thou ſhalt be old, thou ſhalt ſtretch forth thy hands, and another ſhall gird thee, and carry thee whither thou wouldſt not; This spake he, ſignifying by what death he ſhould GLORI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FIE God.</hi> So that it ſeems, thoſe that have ſo much Courage, as to ſuffer chearfully for the Name of Chriſt, and to lay down their lives for the ſake of Chriſt, their Death and Sufferings will tend much to the Glory of God, and to the Eternal Bliſſe and Happineſs of their own Souls.</p>
            <p>Therefore when our Enemies ſhall threaten us, and command us to <hi>ſpeak nor preach no more in the Name of Jeſus,</hi> nor <hi>Meet</hi> any more to <hi>Worſhip</hi> God in his <hi>own way;</hi> Let us (with <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi>) ask them, <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God, to hearken unto you, more than unto God, judge ye?</hi> And let us tell them plainly to their faces, <hi>That we muſt obey God rather than Men;</hi> Therefore we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſpeak the things which we have <hi>ſeen</hi> and <hi>heard,</hi> and we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but practiſe the things which we have learned, and received in Command from Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>There are two notable and very remarkable Examples worthy of our Conſideration, which I ſhall briefly urge, for our Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this matter: The one is concerning the three <hi>Children,</hi> in <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.16, 17, 18. Oh! that there were but ſuch a ſpirit amongſt the People of God now, in this day of <hi>Sions</hi> bleeding.</p>
            <p>Well, but let us a little conſider how they behaved themſelves; the <hi>King</hi> had made a <hi>Decree,</hi> and given forth <hi>Command,</hi> That all People ſhould fall down and Worſhip the <hi>Golden Image</hi> which he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97238:17"/>he had ſet up, and whoſoever would not, ſhould the ſame hour be caſt into the midſt of a Burning fiery Furnace. Well, but <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> they broke his <hi>Decree,</hi> and diſobeyed his Command, and was not at all afraid of his fury, nor terrified at the puniſhment; and when they were called to an account before the <hi>King</hi> for this their Diſobedience to his <hi>Decree,</hi> he proffered them Pardon upon condition of their now complying; But if not, they muſt expect to feel the effects of his Rage and Fury in the Fiery Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace; and who is that God, that ſhould deliver them out of his hands? Well, now it is come to this with them, they muſt either <hi>Turn,</hi> or <hi>Burn;</hi> they muſt either Bow to the Image, or be Burnt in the Fire; they muſt either conform with their Bodies to the Kings Command, or elſe expoſe their Bodies to the Burning Flames. Well, and how did they behave themſelves in this Caſe? See the ſtory, and you ſhall find it at large, <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and ſaid to the <hi>King (O Nebuchadnezzar) we are not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to anſwer thee in this matter;</hi> If it be ſo, <hi>our God whom we ſerve, is able to deliver us from the Burning Fiery Furnace; and he will deliver us out of thine hand (O King.)</hi> But now, Herein conſiſts chiefly the Excellency of their Spirit, in the next words, therefore mark; <hi>But if not,</hi> whether God will deliver us or no; <hi>Yet be it known unto thee, (O King) that we will not ſerve thy gods, nor worſhip the Golden Image which thou haſt ſet up.</hi> Here's an admirable Spirit for the ſervice of God, full of Confidence and Reſolution, for the Glory of the true and living God; As much as if they ſhould ſay; If it be ſo <hi>(O King)</hi> do thy worſt, we matter it not; our God whom we ſerve is able to deliver us; and he will deliver us from thy Rage and Cruelty, <hi>(O King)</hi> therefore we are not careful to anſwer thee in the Buſineſs; And further we teſtifie unto thee, <hi>(O King)</hi> that whether he will deliver us, or not deliver us; whether we Burn, or not Burn; come Life, or come Death; yet we would have thee to know <hi>(O King)</hi> that we will <hi>not ſerve thy Gods, nor we will not worſhip the Golden Image which thou haſt ſet up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh therefore now let us endeavour to bear upon our hearts the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> of theſe three Famous <hi>Children,</hi> (or rather <hi>Champions</hi>) of the moſt High God; That we may through their example, be provoked and Encouraged, to hold faſt the <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, even in the worſt Condition that may befall us, that ſo <hi>being Faithfull unto
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97238:18"/>Death, we may receive the Crown of Life, and ſit with Chriſt in his Throne and Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another <hi>Example</hi> that I ſhall take notice of, for our Conſideration and Encouragement, is concerning <hi>Paul,</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 21.13. which indeed is very Remarkable, and worthy of our obſervation and practiſe. <hi>Paul,</hi> it ſeems, had ſome Work to do for God at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and was much preſſed in Spirit, to go, and bear witneſs to the Name of Jeſus there; But it ſeems before he went, he was foretold in a Figure, how he ſhould <hi>Suffer</hi> when he came there; and how he ſhould be delivered into the hands of <hi>Perſecutors;</hi> for there was a certain Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet named <hi>Agabus,</hi> came down from <hi>Judea,</hi> and when he was come among the Diſciples, he took <hi>Pauls</hi> Girdle, and Bound his own hands and Feet with it; and Propheſied in the Spirit, that ſo the Jews at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhould bind the Man that owed that Girdle, and ſhould deliver him into the hands of the Gentiles; And when the Diſciples heard that, they began to perſwade him, and earneſtly entreat him, not to go to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and laid before him the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of his <hi>Sufferings,</hi> thinking to prevent him of his Journey. Well, but what doth <hi>Paul</hi> do in this Caſe? Doth he neglect the Work of the Lord to avoid his <hi>Sufferings?</hi> Doth he forbear to go, becauſe of Danger? No, its almoſt Death to him to think of forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and leaving the Work of the Lord undone at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> what ever it Coſts him: Therefore ſaid he in his Anſwer to his Diſciples; <hi>What mean you to Weep, and to Break my heart?</hi> As much as if he ſhould ſay; what mean you to be thus earneſt, to hinder me from the Work of the Lord; away with all your Entreaties, and away with all your Perſwaſions; for I am more afflicted and wounded in heart, at the Conſideration of your perſwaſions (in this Caſe) than I am at the Conſideration of all my <hi>Sufferings</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> For I would have you to think that I am Ready, not onely to be <hi>Bound,</hi> but alſo to <hi>Dye at Jeruſalem, for the Name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that this valiant Spirit of <hi>Pauls,</hi> were but Seated and Grounded in the hearts of all Profeſſors at this Day; how would it Glorifie God, and make his Truth and Goſpel ſhine in the World, and mightily amaze, and aſtoniſh the hearts of our Enemies, and exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly Engage the Lord, to Crown us ſpeedily with Victory and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance!</p>
            <p>Therefore now let us ſeriouſly weigh theſe things, and lay them to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97238:18"/>heart; And let us Rouſe up our Dull Spirits, and be Valiant for God, and the more our Adverſaries increaſe in their Rage and Fury againſt us, the more let us increaſe in our Zeal and Courage for Chriſt; and let us Remember the Lord is with us, and for us; and if we continue Faithful to him, <hi>he will never leave us, nor forſake us,</hi> But continually Support us, and Comfort us, and in his due time deliver us out of all our Troubles and Afflictions.</p>
            <p>Therefore to conclude this point, <hi>Let us be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the Power of his might,</hi> and <hi>take unto our ſelves the whole Armour of God, That we may be able to ſtand, and withſtand, in this evil Day;</hi> That ſo having <hi>fought a good Fight, and having finiſhed our Courſe, and kept the Faith, we may at length receive that Crown of Righteouſneſs, and that Eternal weight of Glory, which is laid up for all thoſe that love the Appearing of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with this point of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and ſhall now come to the laſt Branch of the Text, wherein is comprehended the third and laſt <hi>Obſervation,</hi> which I raiſed from the words; I ſhall now endeavour to Manage and Proſecute that, as the Lord ſhall direct me.</p>
            <p>Therefore I proceed and ſay; <hi>That it is the good pleaſure of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, to provide and prepare a Kingdom for his People.</hi> The Lord hath ſo much Love and Affection for his People, as that he takes Delight and Pleaſure in their Glory and Happineſs; therefore he will be ſure to have ſo much Care and Tender Reſpect towards them, as to provide a Reward for his Flock; And their Reward ſhall be no leſs than a <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Kingdom:</hi> I ſay, it is the good Pleaſure of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God to provide an Eminent Reward for his People; yea to prepare a <hi>Kingdom</hi> for his deſpiſed little Flock; <hi>Fear not little Flock, for it's your Father's good Pleaſure to give you the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though poſſibly now, they may not be counted worthy of a poor contemptible Cottage by the Men of the World, yet the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf will one Day count them worthy of a <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Kingdom;</hi> though now (it may be) they are not counted fit to have a being in the World, yet the LORD will one Day count them fit to have a Being in a Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Kingdom;</hi> though now (it may be) they are ſo much deſpiſed by the World, as that they are not counted worthy to dwell amongſt Sinful Men upon Earth, yet they are ſo much honoured by the Lord, as that he will one day count them worthy to dwell with Glorious Angels in Heaven; though now (it may be) they are poor, and deſpiſed and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97238:19"/>trampled under Foot, yet they ſhall one Day be Rich and Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and ſit upon Thrones; Though now (it may be) they are cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with Reproach, and covered with ſhame, yet they ſhall one Day be cloathed with Majeſty, and Crown'd with Glory; though now (it may be) they are toſſed to and fro, and have no certain dwelling place, yet they ſhall one Day enjoy a <hi>City which hath Foundations, whoſe Builder and Maker is God.</hi> Here's a Glorious Portion laid up in ſtore for the poor deſpiſed Flock of Chriſt; Here's that which will abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly make them amends for all their Sorrow and Travel in their Earthly Pilgrimage; though now (poſſibly) they are counted the filth and the off-ſcouring of the World; yet the very pooreſt and meaneſt of God's People, ſhall one day be promoted, and advanced to an Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Kingdom;</hi> I ſay a <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhall one Day be the Portion of the pooreſt and meaneſt of Gods People; yea, even thoſe that are the moſt deſpiſed, and moſt abuſed, are no leſs than <hi>Heirs</hi> of a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> they have it now in promiſe, and they ſhall aſſuredly one Day have it in poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>But for the better Confirmation of this Glorious Truth, I ſhall endeavour to give you ſome Scripture-Teſtimonies which ſtrongly bear witneſs thereunto; See one in Mat. 25.34. <hi>Then ſhall the King ſay to them on his right hand,</hi> (which is his little Flock, being then Separated from the Goats) <hi>Come ye Bleſſed of my Father,</hi> (A Glorious Invitation indeed) he doth not onely invite them to come, <hi>But, come ye BLESSED;</hi> Why what's the matter? Wherein doth their Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs conſiſt? See the next words, and you ſhall find; <hi>Inherit the KINGDOM, prepared for you from the Foundation of the World:</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doth their Bleſſedneſs conſiſt, and herein are they Bleſſed Perſons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. It was the good pleaſure of Almighty God to provide and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a Kingdom for them, &amp; now they are called to come and poſſeſſe it; therefore this is one clear Scripture Teſtimony, to prove the Truth of this <hi>Propoſition;</hi> namely, <hi>That it is the good pleaſure of Almighty God, to provide and prepare a Kingdom for his People.</hi> See another, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.10. Where our Saviour Chriſt ſpeaks this Language; <hi>Bleſſed are they which are Perſecuted for Righteouſneſs ſake; for theirs is the KINGDOM of Heaven,</hi> (Mark) <hi>Bleſſed are they which are PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SECUTED for Righteouſneſs ſake:</hi> Though in a PERSECUTED State, yet in a BLESSED State: though in troubled Condition, yet in a happy Condition: Why ſo? How doth it appear, that they are
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97238:19"/>Bleſſed in a Perſecuted State? Why here's the buſineſs; there is a <hi>Kingdom-Portion</hi> prepared, to make them amends for their <hi>Suffering-Portion;</hi> therefore though they may be Perſecuted, and Reproached, and evil ſpoken of, yet their Condition is bleſſed and happy, Becauſe their <hi>Reward ſhall be great in the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas now we are but ſtrangers and Pilgrims, Travelling towards our Fathers houſe, and we muſt expect to meet with many Rubs and difficult ſteps in our Journey; we muſt expect to meet with many Storms, and bitter Blaſts in our way to Heaven, and to climb over many troubleſome ſtiles, before we come to the Land of Reſt; But when we come home to our own Country, and Arrive at our continuing City; Then we ſhall receive a Glorious Portion from the hands of our Heavenly Father, which will be no leſs than a <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See another Glorious Teſtimony for the Truth of this Propoſition, in <hi>Luke</hi> 22.28, 29, 30. Says Chriſt there to his Diſciples, <hi>Ye are they which have continued with me in my Temptations.</hi> As much as if he ſhould ſay; you are they which have been with me in all my Troubles, and have followed me faithfully in all my Sufferings, and have Travelled with me in a difficult path; and now, for your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Encouragement, here's a promiſe for you, to make you amends for all your Tryals, I'le ſee that you ſhall be ſufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited for every thing that you have loſt in my ſervice; Therefore take notice, <hi>That I appoint unto you a Kingdom, even as my Father hath appointed unto me;</hi> And you ſhall <hi>eat and drink at my Table in my Kingdom, and ſit upon Thrones Judging the twelve Tribes of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, what Honour and Dignity, what Glory and Majeſty, the poor deſpiſed Saints of God ſhall one Day have conferred upon them; and what an Eminent Portion they ſhall one Day receive from the hands of their Heavenly Father: therefore, <hi>Here</hi> they have no <hi>continuing City,</hi> But they <hi>ſeek one to come:</hi> Wherefore God is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to be called <hi>their God;</hi> for he hath prepared for them a <hi>City.</hi> Therefore I ſhall conclude the proof of this <hi>Propoſition,</hi> with that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtle, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.5. where he ſpeaks thus; <hi>Hearken my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Brethren; Hath not God choſen the poor of this World, rich in Faith, and Heirs of the Kingdom, which he hath promiſed to them that love him.</hi> Though they are poor in this World, yet they are rich in Faith, and Heirs of a <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and though now, (it may be) they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97238:20"/>are Branded and Stigmatiſed with filthy names, and called <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and the like; yet they ſhall one day appear to be the Jewels of God, and <hi>all Nations ſhall call them Bleſſed, in a delightful Land;</hi> and they <hi>ſhall dwell</hi> with God in his <hi>heavenly habitation; For this we know, when our Earthly Tabernacle is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, we ſhall have a Building of God, an houſe not made with hands, Eternal in the Heavens, Mal.</hi> 3.12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.</p>
            <p>So much ſhall ſuffice for the proof of this <hi>Propoſition,</hi> viz. <hi>That Gods People ſhall one Day Receive, Poſſeſſe, and enjoy a Kingdom.</hi> I ſhall now come, to ſpeak a few words concerning the <hi>Excellency</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and endeavour to ſhew you (in ſome meaſure) what manner of <hi>Kingdom</hi> this will be, that ſhall one Day be the <hi>Portion</hi> of Gods People.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which God will one Day give unto his People, <hi>It is a Heavenly Kingdom:</hi> It is not an Earthly corruptible Kingdom, Adorned with worldly Vanities; But it is a Heavenly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible Kingdom, Adorned with Celeſtial Majeſty: It is not a mean contemptible Kingdom, attended with Earthly corruption; But it is a High and Lofty Kingdom, filled with Heavenly Beauty: It is not an ordinary Kingdom, to be found here upon Earth; But it is an Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Kingdom, reſerved now in Heaven; It is ſuch a Kingdom, as all the Kingdoms on Earth, and all the <hi>Monarchs</hi> in the World, are not worthy to be compared, nor put in the Ballance with it: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is one thing which may (in a great meaſure) Demonſtrate the <hi>Excellency</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom;</hi> It is ſuch a Heavenly Portion, as that all the Earth, is not able to afford ſuch a precious Jewel. See what the Scripture ſayes concerning this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> in this very particular, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.18. Sayes the Apoſtle there, <hi>The Lord ſhall deliver me from every evil work, and will preſerve me unto his HEAVENLY King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> (Mark) <hi>he will preſerve me</hi> not onely unto <hi>his Kingdom,</hi> but unto his <hi>HEAVENLY Kingdom;</hi> An excellent Kingdom, of a Heavenly Nature, nothing on Earth comparable thereunto. Therefore ſayes Chriſt alſo, Mat. 5.3, 10, 12. <hi>Bleſſed are the poor in Spirit, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven: Bleſſed are they which are Perſecuted for Righteouſneſs ſake, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in Heaven.</hi> So that it is not onely a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> but a <hi>Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> it is not onely a <hi>Reward,</hi> but a <hi>Reward in Heaven;</hi> it is not onely a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97238:20"/>
               <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but a <hi>Heavenly Jeruſalem, Heb.</hi> 12.22. It is not onely a <hi>Country,</hi> but a <hi>Heavenly Country, Heb.</hi> 11.16. It is not onely a <hi>Building,</hi> but a <hi>Building</hi> in the <hi>Heavens,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.1. <hi>A City which hath Foundations, whoſe Builder and Maker is God, Heb.</hi> 11.10. So that this is the firſt thing, that beſpeaks the <hi>Excellency</hi> of this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> It is a <hi>Heavenly Kingdom,</hi> A Portion which this World is not able to afford.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is a <hi>Gloriom Kingdom,</hi> or a Kingdom of <hi>Glory;</hi> It is not onely a Heavenly Kingdom, But a <hi>Glorious Heavenly Kingdom,</hi> or a <hi>Heavenly Glorious Kingdom;</hi> It is not a Kingdom mixt with worldly pollutions, but it is a Kingdom filled with Heavenly <hi>Glory;</hi> It is not a vile Kingdom, attended with ſhame and diſhonour, But it is a pretious Kingdom, full of Honour and <hi>Glory;</hi> It is ſuch a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as all the Kingdoms on Earth, are not worthy to be compared with it for Glory and Beauty; there's no Kingdom on Earth, ſo Glorious, out it's mixt with ſome ſhame and contempt; But the Saints Kingdom, is altogether lovely, cloathed with Glory and Majeſty; there is no Kingdom on Earth, ſo Beautiful, but it's mixt with ſome ſilthineſs, and Deformity; but the Saints Kingdom, is altogether comely, full of Spendour and Beauty; there is no Kingdom on Earth ſo pleaſant, but it's mixt with ſome filth and corruption; but the Saints Kingdom, is altogether pure, full of Excellent Brightneſs. Oh the Excellency and Purity of this Kingdom! Oh the Glory, and Dignity of this Kingdom! who is ſufficient to expreſſe the Majeſty and Beauty of this Kingdom? The tongue of Men and Angels is not able to ſpeak forth the fulneſs thereof.</p>
            <p>But now to prove, That it is ſuch a Glorious Kingdom; ſee firſt that ſaying of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>You know</hi> (ſays Paul) <hi>how we exhorted and charged every one of you, That you would walk worthy of God, who hath called you unto his Kingdom and GLORY:</hi> (Mark) he hath not onely called you to his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> but to his <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>GLORY;</hi> (that is to ſay) to that <hi>Glory</hi> which is in that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which plainly ſhews it is a <hi>GLORIOUS Kingdom.</hi> And further it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the greateſt Glory, and the greateſt Excellency that this World can afford, is not worthy to be compared with the <hi>GLORY</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom;</hi> For the Spirit of God in Scripture, doth frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call the greateſt Glory, and the greateſt Honour of this World, <hi>But vanity and vexation of Spirit,</hi> and it's of no Eſteem in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97238:21"/>count of God and good Men; but the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in this Text, Reckons it a great Priviledge, and a wonderful happineſs, to have an Intereſt in this <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>GLORY; Therefore he ſtrictly charged them, to walk worthy,</hi> or ſutable to that great <hi>Love of God, which had graciouſly called them to ſuch a GLORIOUS Kingdom;</hi> And further ſaith he, in another place, Rom. 8.18. <hi>I Reckon that the Sufferings of this preſent time, are not worthy to be compared with the GLORY which ſhall be revealed.</hi> There will be ſuch Ineſtimable Glory revealed, in and for the Saints, when they enjoy this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; as there is nothing comparable thereunto there is nothing here below worth the naming in compariſon thereof. Therefore ſayes he in another place, 2 Cor 4.17. <hi>Our Light affliction, which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding, and Eternal weight of GLORY:</hi> So that this is alſo another thing, which doth very much Demonſtrate the <hi>Excellency</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom;</hi> It is not onely a <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Kingdom,</hi> but a <hi>Heavenly Kingdom of GLORY;</hi> And there is a <hi>Crown of Glory</hi> in it, laid up for all the <hi>Little Flock of Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 3, 4. verſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, It is an <hi>unmoveable Kingdom,</hi> or a <hi>Kingdom</hi> which cannot be <hi>moved;</hi> It is ſuch a Kingdom as can never be ſhaken nor moved, by all the Powers on Earth; nor it can never be thrown down nor deſtroyed, by all the ſtrength in the World; All the Force and Violence, that men and Devils can uſe againſt it, can never ſhake nor move the Foundation of this <hi>Kingdom;</hi> It far exceeds all the Kingdoms on Earth in this particular alſo: For alas, all the Kingdoms on Earth, are Changeable, and Mutable, and are very ſubject to be ſubdued, and deſtroyed, by Power and ſtrength; But the Saints <hi>Kingdom,</hi> is Unchangeable, and Immutable, an <hi>Inheritance which fadeth not away.</hi> Alas the Kingdoms of this World are at no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, they are often altering and changing in their affairs; Sometimes to one thing, and ſometimes to another; ſometimes High and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Low; ſometimes Rich, and ſometimes Poor; ſometimes Gaining, and ſometimes Loſing; ſometimes Peace, and ſometimes War; ſometimes Proſperity, and ſometimes Adverſity; Alwayes Ebbing and Flowing; Riſing and Falling; Changing and Turning, from one thing to another; Till many times, <hi>Kings</hi> are even weary of their Kingdoms. And again, in the Kingdoms of this World, things are ſo Mutable, and ſubject to Change, that it's poſſible a man
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97238:21"/>may be a <hi>King</hi> to day, and a <hi>Beggar</hi> to morrow; a man may be upon the Throne to day, and upon the Dunghil to morrow; a man may be in great Honour to day, and in great Reproach to morrow; yea, a man may be a <hi>Ruler</hi> to day, and over-ruled himſelf to morrow: ſo variable and changable are even the beſt things of this life: By which means all things here below, are but <hi>vanity and vexation of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> But now it is not ſo in the <hi>Saints Kingdom,</hi> it's altogether Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movable and Unchangable, there's nothing can alter or change the <hi>Excellency</hi> of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> there's nothing can ſtain the Glory, nor diminiſh the Beauty of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> but as it is a <hi>Heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> now, ſo it will be a <hi>Heavenly Kingdom</hi> for EVER; and as it is a <hi>Glorious Kingdom</hi> now, ſo it will be a <hi>Glorious Kingdom</hi> for <hi>Ever;</hi> and as it is full of Beauty and Majeſty now, ſo it will be full of Beauty and Majeſty for EVER: So that this is alſo another thing, which doth exceedingly proclaim the <hi>Excellency</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom;</hi> Therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Wherefore we receiving a Kingdom which cannot be MOVED, let us hold faſt Grace, whereby we may ſerve God acceptably with Reverence and godly Fear:</hi> (Mark) not only a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> but a <hi>Kingdom which CANNOT be MOVED;</hi> not only a <hi>Building,</hi> but an <hi>ETERNAL Building,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.1. not only a <hi>City,</hi> but a <hi>City which hath FOUNDATIONS, whoſe Builder and Maker is God,</hi> Heb. 11.10. not only an <hi>Inheritance,</hi> but an <hi>INCORRUPTIBLE Inheritance, which fadeth not away,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.4.</p>
            <p>So that theſe three things ſeriouſly conſidered, do exceedingly diſcover the unſpeakable <hi>Excellency</hi> of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which the Saints and People of God ſhall one day receive for their <hi>Reward</hi> and <hi>Portion.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, It is a <hi>HEAVENLY Kingdom.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, It is a <hi>GLORIOUS Kingdom.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, It is an <hi>UNMOVABLE Kingdom.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Which being put together, make a <hi>HEAVENLY, GLORI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUS, UNMOVABLE Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An excellent Habitation, an appointed Portion, a precious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for the People of God.</p>
            <p>So much ſhall ſuffice concerning the <hi>Excellency</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom</hi> it ſelf: I ſhall now come to ſpeak ſomething concerning the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of God's People in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and endeavour to give you a glimpſe, or a Diſcovery of that Glory and Happineſs, which the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97238:22"/>Saints ſhall be made partakers of in this <hi>Heavenly, Glorious, Unmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Happineſs and Priviledges of God's People in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> conſiſt in theſe two general Heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, A <hi>Freedome from all Evill.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, An <hi>Enjoyment of all Good.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>But more particularly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They ſhall be all Righteous, and without Sin; they ſhall be altogether pure, and without ſpot; they ſhall be altogether clean, and without Corruption; they ſhall be altogether Holy, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Pollution: This is a glorious State, and one excellent Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the Saints ſhall be made partakers of in this Heavenly Kingdom; They ſhall be wholly freed from Sin and Iniquity, and put out of a Capacity of ever Sinning more; Oh! this is a bleſſed Priviledge indeed, and much to be deſired and longed after; Oh! ſaith many a gracious Soul, If I were but altogether free from Sin and Iniquity, I ſhould think my ſelf in a happy Condition indeed: Oh! If I were but in ſuch a State, as that I could never Sin againſt God, what a bleſſed Condition ſhould I be in? But this is ſuch a Condition, as cannot be attained on this ſide the Grave; this is ſuch a Priviledge, as cannot be found in an Earthly Pilgrimage; for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! now we are ſubject to Sin every day, and lyable to fall into Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity every hour, and many Temptations offer themſelves unto us, and ſpread themſelves before us, and many times occaſion us to Sin againſt the Lord, and endanger the deſtruction of our Souls: But now when the Saints enjoy this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> they ſhall be altogether free from Sin and Iniquity, and perfectly Pure and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled before the Lord; And all Temptations, and all occaſions of Sin, ſhall be wholly removed and taken away, and they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be in a Capacity to Sin any more againſt the Lord; but they ſhall be all a <hi>Tree of Righteouſneſs,</hi> planted by the pure hand of the Lord; And there ſhall be no more Curſe, but the Throne of God and of the Lamb, ſhall be in it, and his Servants ſhall Reign, and ſerve him for Ever and Ever, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.3, 5. See alſo, <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.5. <hi>And in their mouth was found no guile, for they are WITHOUT FAULT before the Throne of God:</hi> There's nothing of GUILT to be laid to their Charge; there's nothing of BLAME to be found amongſt them; there's none can accuſe them of any FAULT: <hi>But they are altogether RIGHTEOUS without SIN, and they ſhall inherit
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97238:22"/>the Land for Ever, that God may be Glorified,</hi> Iſa. 60.21.</p>
            <p>This is one great <hi>Priviledge,</hi> and one Branch of that Happineſs, which the Saints ſhall be made partakers of in this <hi>HEAVENLY Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> Another is this.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They ſhall be wholly freed from all Sorrow, and from all Trouble of what nature ſoever; they ſhall be wholly freed from all manner of Grief and Anguiſh; from all manner of Diſtreſs and Miſery, and they ſhall never know what belongs to Sorrow any more: Alas! now we are ſubject to much Sorrow and Miſery, to much Trouble and Diſtreſs, and many diſtempers of Body, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Nature, do dayly attend us; and ſeveral Afflictions are every day ready to ſeize upon us, as Sickneſs, Lameneſs, Blindneſs, Hunger and Cold, and many other Troubles and Miſeries, are eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day ready to fall upon the outward man in this life, which many times occaſion great grief and ſorrow of heart, and great trouble and perplexity of ſpirit, and great complainings under the burthen of bitter Afflictions; But now it is not ſo in this <hi>Heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> for when the Saints receive their Portion there, then all Sorrow and Trouble ſhall quite be removed, and all occaſions of Grief and Anguiſh ſhall be wholly taken away; and there ſhall be no more cauſe of Complaint under the burthen of any Affliction, nor no more cauſe of Grief under the ſence of any Miſery; <hi>for they ſhall hunger no more, neither ſhall they thirſt any more,</hi> neither ſhall the Sun light on them, nor any heat, for the <hi>Lamb</hi> which is in the midſt of the <hi>Throne</hi> ſhall <hi>feed them,</hi> and ſhall <hi>lead them into Fountains of living Waters;</hi> and God ſhall wipe away all <hi>Tears</hi> from their eyes; and there ſhall be no more Death, nor no more Sorrow, nor no more <hi>Crying;</hi> neither ſhall there be any more <hi>Pain,</hi> for all ſuch things ſhall be paſt'd away, and ſhall never have a Being in this <hi>Heavenly Kingdom,</hi> Revel. 7.16, 17. &amp; 21.4.</p>
            <p>Here's another <hi>excellent Priviledge,</hi> that the Saints ſhall be made partakers of in this glorious <hi>Kingdom;</hi> they ſhall never any more taſte of Sorrow, nor never any more be acquainted with Grief; they ſhall never any more be troubled with Afflictions, nor never any more fall under Diſtreſs; though now (it may be) they may be laden with Afflictions, and burthened with Miſery, yet the time will come, when Afflictions ſhall fly away, and Miſery ſhall be no more; <hi>For all Trouble ſhall be ſwallowed up in Victory, and the Lord
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97238:23"/>God will wipe away Tears from off all Faces, and the rebuke of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall be wholly taken away; for the Lord hath ſpoken it,</hi> Iſa. 25.8.</p>
            <p>Oh! what an Eminent <hi>Priviledge</hi> will this be, for poor deſpiſed Saints to be made partakers of! Oh! what a bleſſed condition will they be in, that are ſubjects of this <hi>Glorious Kingdom!</hi> There is no condition on Earth ſo happy, nor no State in the World ſo Excellent, nor no enjoyment under the Sun, worthy to be compared with the leaſt Priviledge in this <hi>Heavenly Kingdom;</hi> there is no condition on Earth ſo happy, but it's ſubject to miſery; there is no condition on Earth ſo joyful, but its ſubjects to ſorrow; there is no condition on Earth ſo pleaſant, but it is ſubject to pain; but now the Saints in their Kingdom, ſhall be wholly delivered from all their afflictions, and ſhall never know what belongs to Trouble any more; They ſhall be wholly exempted from all their Infirmities, and be crowned with Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, without any change.</p>
            <p>So that this is another <hi>Excellent Priviledge,</hi> or a ſecond Branch of that Happineſs, which the Saints ſhall be made partakers of in this <hi>Heavenly Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Another is this.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They ſhall dwell with God and Chriſt, and ſee them Face to Face; they ſhall be received into the preſence of God, and behold his Glory; and they ſhall ſit down in the preſence of the Lamb and behold his Beauty; they ſhall be ſo much honoured by God, and promoted by Jeſus Chriſt, as to be Companions with them in Glory, and dwell in their preſence continually. Here's another <hi>Excellent Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge,</hi> and Emninent Dignity; which the Saints ſhall be made partakers of in this Glorious <hi>Kingdom.</hi> They ſhall not onely be freed from ſhame and reproach, but they ſhall alſo be Crowned with Honour and Dignity, Their eyes ſhall not onely be freed from vain ſights, and Terrible objects; but they ſhall alſo be Bleſſed with Heavenly Viſions, and Sights of God, and dwell in the preſence of the Lamb continually. It's counted a great Honour, and an Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Priviledge, (amongſt the Men of the World) to behold the face of an Earthly King, or to be admitted into the preſence of a great Perſon; But it's counted more Honour, to be one of the Family and DWELL in his Preſence, and to be a Companion with Him in his Honour and Dignity. But now, the Saints in their <hi>Kingdom,</hi> ſhall have tenfold more Honour and Dignity than all this; (I mean in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97238:23"/>Reference to this particular, beſides all the Reſt) they ſhall have more Honour, than to behold the face of an Earthly King; for they ſhall behold the face of him that is <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and Lord of Lords; they ſhall have more Honour, than to be admitted into the preſence of a great Man on Earth, for they ſhall be admitted into the preſence of a Great God in Heaven; And not onely ſo, but they ſhall be of his Family, and DWELL with him, and be Companions with him in his <hi>Glorious Kingdom:</hi> Therefore ſays the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 140.13. <hi>Surely the Righteous ſhall give thanks unto thy Name, The Upright ſhall DWELL in thy preſence.</hi> (Mark) it doth not ſay onely, <hi>They ſhall BE in thy preſence for a Little Time;</hi> But they <hi>ſhall 'DWELL in thy preſence;</hi> They ſhall continue and abide in thy preſence as Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons belonged and related to thy Houſe and Family; And they ſhall ſit at the Table with Jeſus Chriſt, and ſee his Face, and his <hi>Name</hi> ſhall be in their <hi>Foreheads,</hi> and they ſhall be known to be his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants for <hi>Ever, Revel.</hi> 22.4. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.30. Therefore ſayes Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.3. <hi>If I go to prepare a place for you, I will come again, and receive you unto my Self, that where I am, THERE Ye may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</hi> So that it ſeems, where the Lord Chriſt is Exalted, there muſt the Saints be Exalted; And where the Lord Chriſt takes up his habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, there muſt the Saints be received; And they ſhall dwell in his preſence, and ſee him, as he is: Therefore ſayes the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. <hi>Now we ſee through a Glaſs darkly, but then we ſhall ſee face to face: now we know but in part, but then we ſhall know, even as alſo we are known.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that this is alſo another <hi>Excellent Priviledge,</hi> or a third Branch of that Happineſs which the Saints ſhall be made partakers of in this <hi>Heavenly Kingdom.</hi> They ſhall DWELL in the Preſence of the Lord, and continually behold the Majeſty of God.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Another is this.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They ſhall be like unto Jeſus Chriſt in Splendour and Beauty. Their Bodies ſhall be cloathed with glory and Majeſty, like unto the Body of Jeſus Chriſt. As Chriſt is Glorious and Beautiful, ſo ſhall the Saints be Glorious and Beautiful; and as Chriſt is fair and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo ſhall the Saints be fair and comely; and as Chriſt is pleaſant and altogether Lovely, ſo ſhall the Saints be pleaſant, and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether Lovely; and there ſhall be no ſpot of Deformity in them, nor no Infirmity nor Blemiſh upon them; But they ſhall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97238:24"/>ſhine in Beauty, like the brightneſs of the Firmament, and exceed the Stars in Luſtre and Purity. Here's another <hi>Excellent Priviledge,</hi> and a lovely Branch of heavenly Happineſs, wonderful to conſider of, and Marvellous pleaſant will it be to enjoy the ſame. It's counted a great Honour, and a high Priviledge, amongſt the People of the World, to be but a little Adorned with Earthly Beauty, or to have but a comely Face, Garniſhed with a little Natural Brightneſs; yea, many times it is ſo highly eſteemed, and counted ſuch a Rare Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as it makes many Perſons proud, and high-minded, Becauſe of their Earthly Beauty, and becauſe of a comely Face: but alas, this is nothing in compariſon of that Glory and Beauty, which the Saints ſhall be Adorned withall, when they enjoy this <hi>Heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> this is not worthy to be named, in compariſon of that Purity and Comelineſs, which ſhall be the Saints Portion in their Fathers Kingdom; they ſhall have greater Honour, than to be Adorned with Earthly Beauty, and Natural Comelineſs, for they ſhall be Adorned with Heavenly Beauty, and cloathed with Celeſtial Majeſty; yea, they ſhall be Equal unto the Angels for Splendour, and like unto Jeſus Chriſt for Glory. Therefore ſayes the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20, 21. <hi>Our Converſation is in Heaven, from whence alſo we look for our Saviour the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall change our vile Bodies, that they may be faſhionod like unto his GLORIOUS Body; according to the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whereby he is able even to ſubdue all things unto himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though now they are vile bodies, attended with earthly corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet then they ſhall be precious Bodies, attended with Heavenly GLORY; though now they are defiled Bodies, attended with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Infirmities; yet then they ſhall be Lovely Bodies, attended with perfect Purity, and mightily Adorned with Excellent Beauty. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſays Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.43. <hi>Then ſhall the Righteous SHINE forth as the SUN in the Kingdom of their Father.</hi> (Mark) here's glorious Beauty, and wonderful Brightneſs; Here's Eminent Purity, and Heavenly Splendour, <hi>the Righteous ſhall Shine like the SUN in the Kingdom of their Father,</hi> even whilſt others are weeping and wailing in a Furnace of Fire. Oh what unſpeakable Glory, and Excellent Majeſty is here prepared, for poor deſpiſed contemptible Creatures! Oh! how happy and bleſſed, will all thoſe be, that ſhall be counted worthy of this Kingdom and Glory! All the Pleaſure and Glory on Earth, is not worthy to be compared with one Branch of this Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97238:24"/>Happineſs: All the Honour and Beauty under the Sun, is not able to Parrallel the leaſt Glimpſe of this Heavenly Glory. See one notable Text more for this, and ſo I ſhall leave this Particular, and proceed to another, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. Where the Apoſtle is giving a ſhort diſcovery of the Honour and Dignity of the Saints, both here, and hereafter; <hi>Beloved</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>now we are the Sons of God, and it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be:</hi> (Mark) Though we have ſo much Honour and Dignity conferred upon us now at preſent, as to be called the Sons of God, and though the Lord is pleaſed to extend his goodneſs ſo far towards us, now at preſent, as to make us his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by the Spirit of Adoption, yet, it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be; and yet this is ſuch a wonderful Priviledge, as it makes the Apoſtle exceedingly Admire at the Conſideration thereof; Crying out, <hi>BEHOLD</hi> what <hi>MANNER of Love is THIS, that we ſhould be called the Sons of God!</hi> He was mightily filled with Admiration, to conſider of this wonderful Dignity; but yet for all this, <hi>it doth not yet appear, what we ſhall be; for we know, that when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be LIKE him:</hi> (Mark) <hi>we ſhall be like unto Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Bleſſed as he is Bleſſed, Beautiful, as he is Beautiful, Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as he is Glorious; Every way Adorned with Heavenly Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs like unto Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This is alſo another <hi>Excellent Priviledge,</hi> or a fourth Branch of that Happineſs, which the Saints ſhall be made partakers of, in this <hi>Glorious Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Another is this.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They ſhall have wonderful Glorious Company, and bleſſed Society; they ſhall be continually honoured with Heavenly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and bleſſed with Glorious Companions. The meaneſt, and worſt of their Companions, ſhall be Bleſſed and glorious Angels. Though now it may be, they are ſo much deſpiſed by the World, as that they are not counted worthy to dwell in. the Society of wicked Men; yet they are ſo much honoured by the Lord, as that they ſhall one Day be counted worthy to dwell in the Society of Bleſſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and THEY ſhall be their meaneſt Companions. This is another <hi>Glorious Priviledge,</hi> &amp; excellent Dignity, for the People of God in this Heavenly Kingdom, they ſhall never have cauſe to complain of their Company, nor never have cauſe to be weary of their Society; for their meaneſt Company ſhall be glorious Angels, and their worſt Society
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97238:25"/>ſhall be Heavenly Spirits: And indeed this is a Priviledge, which is very acceptable, and delightful unto God's People, and highly eſteemed, and much to be deſired amongſt good men now upon earth, (I mean godly Society) for indeed thoſe that truly fear God, do count it a great Priviledge to enjoy the Society of good People; and would reckon it a great Happineſs, to be wholly and altogether freed from evil company, that they might alwayes enjoy the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of godly People: Therefore ſaith <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 16.3. <hi>My goodneſs extendeth not only unto thee,</hi> (O <hi>Lord</hi>) <hi>but unto thy Saints, and excellent ones, in whom is all my DELIGHT.</hi> But now in this <hi>Heavenly Kingdom,</hi> they ſhall not only have the Society of Saints, and enjoy Communion one with another, without any mixture of Evil; But they ſhall alſo enjoy it with God, and fellowſhip with Jeſus Chriſt, and have the Society of bleſſed and glorious Angels; Therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23. <hi>Ye are come unto Mount Sion, and unto the City of the living God, the Heavenly Jeruſalem, and to an innumerable Company of ANGELS; to the general Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and Church of the Firſt-born, and to God the Judge of all, and to the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect.</hi> Here's Glorious Company, and Heavenly Society; here's pleaſant Companions, and beautiful Partners; here's honourable Equals, and lovely Objects, and all to attend the People of God, to encreaſe their Happineſs in their <hi>Father's Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that this is alſo another <hi>excellent Priviledge,</hi> or a fifth Branch of that Happineſs, which the Saints ſhall be made partakers of in this <hi>Heavenly Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Another is this.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They ſhall have fulneſs of unſpeakable Joy, and fulneſs of Glory and Happineſs; they ſhall be exceedingly filled with Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and wonderfully crowned with Pleaſure; they ſhall not only be freed from Sorrow and Trouble, but they ſhall alſo be filled with Joy and Rejoycing; they ſhall not only be freed from Pain and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, but they ſhall alſo be filled with Delight and Pleaſures; they ſhall not only be freed from Grief, and exempted from Miſery, but they ſhall alſo be exceedingly filled with Comfort, and crowned with Happineſs; they ſhall have Beauty for Aſhes, Joy for Sorrow, Pleaſure for Pain, Glory for Shame, Honour and Dignity, for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and Contempt, the garment of Praiſe, for the ſpirit of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſs; that every way they may be crowned with ſulneſs of Joy,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97238:25"/>and unſpeakable Glory, according to that ſaying of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>In thy Preſence is PULNESSE of Joy, and at thy right hand are Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! the excellent <hi>Priviledge,</hi> and wonderful <hi>Happineſs</hi> of God's People; Oh! how bleſſed are all thoſe that ſhall be counted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to enter into this <hi>Glorious Kingdom?</hi> Who is able to expreſs the Happineſs of Heavenly Subjects? Therefore ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.19. <hi>Oh! how great is thy Goodneſs, which thou haſt laid up for them that fear thee; which thou haſt wrought for them that truſt in him?</hi> (Mark) what unſpeakable language the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> makes uſe of in theſe words, he is not able to expreſs the great Proviſions that the Lord hath laid up in ſtore for his Saints; Therefore ſaith he, <hi>Oh! how great is thy Goodneſs, which thou haſt laid up for them that fear thee?</hi> He wants a tongue to expreſs it, and therefore his heart admires it. See alſo a notable ſaying of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. where it is thus written, <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear hath not heard, neither hath it entered into the heart of man to conceive, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi> (Mark) Here's wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things prepared, here's unſpeakable Glory provided; <hi>Eye hath not ſeen</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>the things which God hath prepared;</hi> and yet the Eye of man hath ſeen many glorious things, and hath beheld many wonderful Objects, and eminent ſhews full of Delight and Pleaſure; but yet the Eye of man hath not ſeen SUCH Things, as God hath prepared for his People: But further, <hi>Ear hath not heard;</hi> yet what wonderful, ſtrange and excellent things, hath been repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Ears of man? Yea, the Ear many times may hear, that which the Eye never hath ſeen; but yet the Ear never heard of <hi>ſuch</hi> Things, as the Lord hath <hi>laid up for his SAINTS:</hi> But yet further, <hi>Neither hath it entered into the heart of man to conceive,</hi> Yet what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable things may the heart of man conceive to it ſelf? What glorious and excellent things may poſſibly enter into the Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the heart? Yea, the heart may fancy to it ſelf, things which are impoſſible to be, and things which cannot be uttered; the heart may conceive that which the Eye never ſaw, nor the Ear never heard; out yet the Heart of man cannot <hi>conceive</hi> SUCH Things, as the Lord hath provided, prepared, and laid up in ſtore for them that love him: The tongue of men and Angels are not able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the FULNES of that Joy, the GREATNES of that Glory, the incomparable Happineſs of Saints in their <hi>Kingdom;</hi> All the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97238:26"/>Joy and Pleaſures on Earth, are but Sorrow and Miſery, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of this Heavenly Joy in the Saints <hi>Kingdom;</hi> All the Glory on Earth, is but Shame and Contempt, in compariſon of the Saints Glory in Heaven; All the Happineſs that can be enjoyed under the Sun, is but Vanity and Trouble, in compariſon of the ſweet and heavenly Happineſs in the Kingdom of Glory: Oh! how may this rejoyce and make glad the ſpirits of Saints, to conſider of their Portion in their <hi>Father's Kingdom;</hi> Oh! how may this raviſh and ſtrengthen the hearts of Gods People, to think of their Fathers love, that he ſhould extend his grace and goodneſs ſo far towards his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as to make them Heirs of a Glorious Kingdom, and crown them with unſpeakable Joy and Happineſs.</p>
            <p>So that this is another <hi>Excellent Priviledge,</hi> or a ſixth branch of that Happineſs which the Saints ſhall enjoy in their Fathers King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Seventhly,</hi> and <hi>Laſtly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. That which is the main thing of all, and that which is moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, is this: All this Glory and Happineſs, and all this Joy and Bleſſedneſs, will be ETERNAL, and ſhall continue, <hi>even for ever and ever:</hi> They ſhall alwayes be glorious, and never know an end of their heavenly Beauty: They ſhall always be bleſſed, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver know an end of their Happineſs; They ſhall alwayes be joyful, and NEVER know an end of Gladneſs; They ſhall alwayes be rich and honourable, and NEVER know an end of their Excellent Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; They ſhall alwayes abound in fulneſs of Joy, and never know an end of their unſpeakable Plenty.</p>
            <p>This is that which doth eminently and chiefly demonſtrate the Excellent Happineſs of the Saints in the Kingdom of Glory; for if they were to enjoy never ſo much Glory and Happineſs, and never ſo much Joy and Bleſſedneſs: yet if this were to continue but for a ſhort time, or a little while, then indeed it would not be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſo much worth the prizing; but the Glory and Happineſs of the Saints in this heavenly Kingdom, is not onely for a little time, but <hi>for ever and ever;</hi> as their Happineſs begins, ſo it ſhall continue, and NEVER have an end: as they ſhall be pure and without ſin at firſt, ſo they ſhall be pure and without ſin for EVER; as they ſhall be freed from ſorrow and trouble at firſt, ſo they ſhall be freed from ſorrow and trouble for EVER; as they ſhall dwell with God and Chriſt at firſt, ſo they ſhall dwell with God and Chriſt for EVER,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97238:26"/>and enjoy the ſociety of glorious Angels to all Eternity. There's nothing can alter nor change the affairs in this Kingdom, nor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can bring the Glory of the Saints to an end. Oh what an incomparable Priviledge is this! where is there ſuch a durable habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in this world, or where is there ſuch a reſting-place on earth? Alas! if the glory of the world do chance to (mile upon a perſon at preſent, and riches and honours do ſeem to encreaſe; all is ſo vain and uncertain, that there's no confidence to be put in their laſting: The world may ſoon ſhew a frowning countenance again, and quickly turn its own glory into ſhame and contempt; and quickly turn riches and plenty into poverty and want, and all may quickly make themſelves wings and vaniſh away, and ſo procure great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vexation of ſpirit. But now in this Kingdom, ALL their Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and all their Priviledges are ETERNAL, and ſhall NEVER have an end: Their Perfection ſhall be ALWAYES compleat, and NEVER be diminiſhed; Their Reward ſhall be SURE, and NE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VER be removed; Their Joy ſhall ALWAYES continue and NE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VER be taken away: But as they are glorious and beautiful at firſt, ſo they ſhall be glorious and beautiful for EVER; and as they are rich and honourable at firſt, ſo they ſhall be rich and honourable for EVER; and as they are bleſſed and happy at firſt, ſo they ſhall be bleſſed and happy for EVER: ALWAYES rejoycing in fulneſs of Glory, and praiſing the Lord to ALL ETERNITY.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſayes the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal.</hi> 16.11. <hi>In thy preſence is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of joy, and at thy right hand are pleaſures for EVERMORE.</hi> So alſo the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> in <hi>Chap.</hi> 61.7. <hi>For their ſhame, they ſhall have double; and for confuſion, they ſhall rejoyce in their portion: they ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Land for EVER, and EVERLASTING Joy ſhall be unto them.</hi> (Mark) Not only Pleaſures, but <hi>Pleaſures for EVERMORE;</hi> not only Joy, but <hi>EVERLASTING Joy:</hi> They ſhall not only have double Glory for all their Shame, and a joyful Portion for all their Confuſion; but it ſhall be of an EVERLASTING nature, and ſhall continue for EVER. There's nothing ſhall be able to diminiſh their Joy, nor nothing ſhall be able to put an end to their Glory; for the portion of Righteouſneſs ſhall be Peace, and the effect thereof AS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SURANCE for EVER. Therefore ſayes Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.46. <hi>The wicked ſhall go into everlaſting puniſhment, but the righteous into life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERNAL.</hi> Again, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall leave or loſe any thing for the ſake of Chriſt, ſhall be ſure to receive a hundred fold, and ſhall inherit EVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LASTING
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97238:27"/>Life, Mat.</hi> 19.29. They ſhall not only have a living portion, and a plentiful reward for all their loſſes and croſſes in this life; but their portion ſhall be an EVERLASTING Portion, and their Reward ſhall continue <hi>for ever and ever.</hi> Therefore ſayes the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.8. <hi>He that ſoweth to the fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reap corruption; but he that ſoweth to the Spirit, ſhall of the Spirit reap Life EVERLASTING.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here's an <hi>Excellent Priviledge,</hi> and a wonderful Portion; here's a bleſſed Reward, and a happy Inheritance: who is able to expreſs the Heavenly happineſs of glorified Saints, in this eternal and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable Kingdom? They ſhall not only be filled with joy, and crowned with glory, but they ſhall ſo continue <hi>for ever and ever,</hi> and enjoy the ſame to all ETERNITY.</p>
            <p>So that all theſe things ſeriouſly conſidered, do exceedingly diſcover the wonderful Happineſs, which the Saints ſhall be made partakers of in this heavenly Kingdom of glory.</p>
            <p>Conſider all theſe branches briefly in order together, and then judge whether you have not great cauſe to admire the goodneſs of God towards his now <hi>Deſpiſed Saints</hi> and People. Although indeed, all that I have ſpoken concerning it, is but a glimpſe (as it were) of that Glory and Happineſs which they ſhall enjoy when they ſhall come to receive the fulneſs of it in their Fathers Kingdom.</p>
            <p>But yet in a Glaſs behold their Happineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They ſhall dwell in a heavenly, glorious, unmoveable Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They ſhall be altogether holy and pure, without ſin and iniquity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They ſhall be wholly freed from all manner of ſorrow and trouble, of what nature ſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> They ſhall dwell in the preſence of God, and of the Lamb, and ſee them face to face, and behold their Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> They ſhall have glorious bodies, full of ſplendor and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, like unto Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> They ſhall have altogether glorious company, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſociety; their meaneſt companions ſhall be heavenly Angels.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> They ſhall have fulneſs of unſpeakable joy, and be exceedingly crowned with unſpeakable happineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> And all this ſhall be eternal, <hi>even for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh taſt and ſee that the Lord is gracious! bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:97238:27"/>Thus having given you a diſcovery (in ſome meaſure) of that Glory and Happineſs which the Saints ſhall enjoy in their Fathers Kingdom. I ſhall now come to make a little Uſe or Application of this comfortable Doctrine, and ſo conclude this Heavenly ſubject.</p>
            <p>Well then, is it ſo, That God is pleaſed to provide and prepare a Kingdom for his People? Then in the next place, by way of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, this will ſerve to diſcover two things to us concerning the People of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It diſcovers the excellency of Gods People; for if it be ſo, That the Lord hath prepared ſuch an excellent Kingdom for his People, and accounts them worthy to enjoy ſuch an excellent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: Oh! then it muſt needs be true, that the People of God are an excellent People, and that they are wonderful high in Gods eſteem. And if it be ſo, that the People of God ſhall be crowned with Glory, and cloathed with Majeſty in a heavenly Kingdom: Oh! then it muſt needs be true, that the People of God are a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious People, and wonderful precious in Gods account. And if it be true, that the People of God ſhall be counted worthy to dwell in his preſence, and behold his Glory; then it appears, that the People of God are an honourable People, and wonderful famous in the ſight of God: Though (it may be) they are much deſpiſed and trampled under foot by the men of this World; yet be it known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all, That there's none in the world ſo excellent as they: And though they are much reproached and branded with ſhame by the men of the world, yet of a truth, there is none in the world ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious as they: And though they are counted the filth and the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of the world, by ungodly people; yet there is none in the world ſo honourable as they: For pray conſider, The pooreſt and meaneſt of Gods People are Princes of Heaven; and they that are moſt deſpiſed, are now Heirs of a glorious Kingdom, and joint heirs with Jeſus Chriſt. It's counted a great honour and dignity amongſt men, to be an earthly Prince, or an Heir to an earthly Kingdom; and he that is Heir to an earthly Crown is counted an excellent Perſon, and worthy of honour and great reſpect: But the meaneſt of Gods People are far more excellent than he, for they are all the Sons and Daughters of the living God, and Heirs with Chriſt to a heavenly Crown and Kingdom. And they are ſo lovely and honourable in the ſight of God, as that he accounts them his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97238:28"/>Jewels, and eſteems them his peculiar Treaſure, and tenders them as he tenders the Apple of his own Eye. This is ſuch an honour and dignity, as all the Kings on earth are not able to reach unto, nor all the Princes &amp; great men under the Sun are not able to claim an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in ſuch an <hi>Excellent Priviledge:</hi> I mean, not by vertue of their earthly power and greatneſs, except they are ſuch as belong to the number of Saints, and ſo inveſted with glory from Heaven. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the meaneſt Saint in the world, is far more excellent and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable than the greateſt Monarch on Earth: Therefore ſayes <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Pſal.</hi> 16.3. <hi>My goodneſs extendeth not unto thee O Lord, but to the Saints that are in the earth, and to the EXCELLENT, in whom is all my delight.</hi> But as touching the wicked, this is his language con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning THEM: <hi>Dogs have compaſſed me about, the aſſembly of the wicked have incloſed me, they are altogether become filthy and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; their POYSON is like the POYSON of a SERPENT; they are like the deaf ADDER, and the filthy BOAR.</hi> Therefore I will not know a wicked perſon, but I will ſay unto them, <hi>Depart from me, ye evil doers, for I will keep the Commandements of my God.</hi> From hence you may obſerve; That wicked perſons (though never ſo great in the eyes of the world) are loathſome and abominable perſons, and very contemptible in the eyes of good men; but the meaneſt Saint is excellent and honourable, and very pretious, both in the ſight of God, and in the account of his People. Therefore little do the fooliſh world think what they do, when they mock and reproach the People of God: And when they ſtrive to perſecute and afflict the Saints, they little think that the Lord takes it as done unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and when they villiſie and abuſe ſuch as are godly, they little think that they are a trampling under foot the Jewels of God, and fighting againſt the Lord: Oh! what enmity do ſuch poor ſouls manifeſt againſt the God of Heaven? Oh! how contrary and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite ſuch perſons are to the living God? For pray conſider, they hate them, but God loves them; they reproach them, but God honours them; they abuſe them, but God vindicates them; they afflict them, but God comforts them; they frown upon them, &amp; pronounce them curſed, but God ſmiles upon them, and proclaims them bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; they rob and ſpoyle them, and endeavour to deprive them of their earthly being, but God takes care of them, and ſatisfies their ſouls with his goodneſs, and will one day crown them with a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Kingdom. Thus the Perſecutors of <hi>Sion</hi> do ſet themſelves
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97238:28"/>againſt the Lord, and oppoſe the mighty God of Jacob.</p>
            <p>They count them odious and filthy, but God counts them excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and honourable. And all this is their priviledge now in this life, before they come to their Crown and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>So that this is the firſt thing that I gather from this Doctrine of the Kingdom: It informs us, that the People of God are an Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, Glorious, and Honourable People.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Secondly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It diſcovers the Happineſs of Gods People. The People of God are not only an Excellent People, but alſo a Happy People: for if it be ſo, that the Lord hath prepared ſuch a glorious Kingdom for his People, and accounts them worthy of ſuch a bleſſed Reward, Oh! then it muſt needs be true, that the People of God are a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py People, and wonderful high in the favour of God. And if it be ſo, that the People of God ſhall have fulneſs of joy and unſpeakable glory, in a Kingdom eternal: Oh! then it appears that the People of God are a bleſſed People, and mightily concerned in the love of the Lord. There's no condition in the world can make them miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, they are alwayes happy, though in the midſt of troubles; they are alwayes bleſſed, though in the midſt of difficulties; they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes rich, though in the midſt of poverty; they are alwayes ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, though in the midſt of hunger; they have alwayes enough to make them joyful, though in the midſt of ſorrows; they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes enough to comfort them, though in the midſt of diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; they have alwayes enough to ſupport them, though in the midſt of weakneſs; they are alwayes at liberty, though in the midſt of bondage: There is nothing in this world can <hi>harm them,</hi> ſo long as they are <hi>followers</hi> of that which <hi>is good,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13.</p>
            <p>Oh! what a wonderful priviledge is this, for travelling Saints to enjoy, for Strangers and Pilgrims to partake of, before they come at their reſt: How doth this exceedingly proclaim the happineſs of Gods People, and the bleſſed condition of all thoſe that belong to Jeſus Chriſt? Oh! how may this comfort and encourage the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful hearts of many ſuffering Saints, and bear up their ſouls in the midſt of Tryals? To conſider, that though the world is their enemy, yet ſtill the Lord is their friend; And though the World hates them, yet ſtill the Lord loves them; And though they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived (it may be) from friends and relations, yet ſtill they have an intereſt in God, and he is their Father, and he is able to make up
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97238:29"/>the loſs of any relation: And though they may want earthly enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and worldly poſſeſſions, yet ſtill they are rich in Promiſes, and Heirs of a Kingdom, and the Lord hath prepared an everlaſting Portion for them. Therefore now, theſe things conſidered, doth exceedingly diſcover the happy condition of Gods People, whilſt they are here on earth in their Pilgrim-ſtate, beſides that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned glory prepared for them in Heaven; for thoſe that can claim an intereſt in this heavenly Portion, are abundantly happy, and continually bleſſed; for its an excellent Fountain, full of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual refreſhment and ſoul-ſatisfaction in the worſt of troubles: Therefore you ſhall find that our Saviour Chriſt doth abundantly proclaim them bleſſed under this very conſideration, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the poor in ſpirit, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven: Bleſſed are they that mourn, for they ſhall be comforted: Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God: Bleſſed are they which are perſecuted for righteouſneſs ſake, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven: Bleſſed are ye when men ſhall revile you, and ſay all manner of evil againſt you falſly for my ſake, for GREAT is your Reward in HEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEN.</hi> So that it ſeems, the conſideration of their future Reward in the Kingdom of Heaven, is that which proclaims them bleſſed and happy now upon earth. Though in a mourning condition, yet in a bleſſed condition; Though in a perſecuted ſtate, yet in a BLESSED ſtate: whatever their condition is, yet they are bleſſed, becauſe their Reward is great in the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            <p>So that this is the ſecond thing, that I gather from this Heavenly Doctrine; It informs us that the People of God are a bleſſed and happy People. Thus much for the firſt <hi>Uſe,</hi> by way of Diſcovery.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> by way of Examination.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Uſe.</hi> Is it ſo, that the Lord hath prepared a Kingdom for his People? Then let US ſeriouſly examine, whether WE have an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in this Kingdom or no? Let US ſearch and try, whether WE have any thing to do with this Heavenly Portion? Or whether WE have any ſhare in this Glorious Reward, or no? For pray conſider ſeriouſly, what will it profit us to hear of a Glorious Kingdom pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Saints, if we have no part nor portion there? Or what will it benefit us to hear of the glory and happineſs of Saints in the Kingdom of Heaven, if it do not belong to us? Alas it will avail us nothing to hear of theſe things, nor to talk of theſe things, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we our ſelves have an intereſt in them, and can call them ours:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97238:29"/>It will do us little good, to hear of the Saints happineſs, if we our ſelves are miſerable: Therefore I ſay, let us take heed, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently examine how it is with us, leſt any root of bitterneſs ſpring up in our ſouls and defile us, and make us unfit for this Glorious Kingdom; for no unclean thing, nor no unrighteous perſon ſhall ever inherit this Heavenly Kingdom. There's none ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the viſions of God, in the Kingdom of Heaven, but ſuch as have clean hands, and a pure heart, and are cleanſed from ſin and iniquity: There's none ſhall receive the Kingdom which cannot be moved, but ſuch as ſerve God acceptably with reverence and godly fear: There's none ſhall dwell in the preſence of God in his Heavenly Habitation, but ſuch as are humble and upright in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: There's none ſhall be happy in Heaven, but ſuch as are holy and heavenly minded on earth; for <hi>without holineſs no man ſhall ſee God;</hi> and <hi>to be carnally minded is death, but to be ſpiritually minded is life and peace.</hi> Therefore let us not flatter our ſelves with vain fancies, nor ſatisfie our ſelves with a bare profeſſion of Godlineſs, nor proclaim peace and ſafety to our ſelves with ſin in our boſoms; for if we do, we ſhall be deceived and undone for ever, <hi>For God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be mocked, but whatſoever a man ſoweth, that he ſhall alſo Reap: And his ſervants ye are to whom you yeeld obedience.</hi> Therefore ſayes Chriſt, <hi>Not every one that ſaith Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, but he that doth the will of my Father which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> (Mark) Not every one that profeſſeth his Name and calls him Lord, but he that lives in obedience to the Will of God: There muſt be a walking with God, as well as a talking of God; There muſt be a DOING the Will of God, as well as a SPEAKING the Will of God. It is not enough to ſay, that Jeſus Chriſt is our Lord, but we muſt make it appear by our actions, and by our obedient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, that he is Lord of our hearts, and that he <hi>Rules and Reigns in our Souls;</hi> for there are a great many that can call Jeſus Chriſt <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> with their tongues, and yet work iniquity with their hands, and intend miſchief in their hearts: But alas! ſuch ſhall never find acquaintance with God at the laſt day, nor never be entertained, nor received into this Heavenly Kingdom; <hi>For every one that names the Name of Chriſt muſt depart from iniquity, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor that which is evil,</hi> or elſe they muſt expect to be denyed by Chriſt, and to depart out of his preſence, as workers of iniquity; and all their profeſſion will be ſo far from doing them any good, as
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97238:30"/>it will rather riſe up in Judgement againſt them, and condemn them at the laſt day: Therefore it highly concerns us all to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ſeriouſly how the caſe ſtands with us, and <hi>to give all diligence to make our Calling and Election ſure, by an humble walking with God,</hi> and by a conſtant perſevering in the pure wayes of the Lord, leſt we ſhould deceive our own ſouls, and miſs of his Glorious Reward in this Heavenly Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And if upon Examination we find our ſelves to be in Gods way, ſtanding upon a ſure foundation, then we may rejoyce in the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, and ſatisfie our ſouls at this Heavenly Fountain; and ſo long as we continue faithful to God in purity of ſoul, we may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge an intereſt in this Heavenly Portion, and call the Kingdom and all its glory ours; and <hi>all the Promiſes of God in Chriſt Jeſus, are Yea, and Amen to us, that by them we might be encouraged to continue and perſevere in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs all the dayes of our lives, to the praiſe and glory of him who hath called us to this Heavenly Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now give me leave to intermix a word of Caution into this <hi>Uſe</hi> of <hi>Examination,</hi> and that is this: If upon right Examination, we find that we have an intereſt in this Glorious Kingdom, Then let us take heed that we do not turn aſide out of the wayes of God, and travel again in the paths of iniquity, and ſo loſe our intereſt, and be deprived of that Kingdom which once we had a right unto. Let us take heed that the Devil do not beguile us with his golden baits of ſin and iniquity, and ſo rob us of our Heavenly Portion. Let us take heed that we do not fell our Heavenly Birth-right for a little worldly pottage, nor change our Heavenly Kingdom for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle earthly profit or worldly advantage: I ſay, let us take heed of theſe things, leſt there ſhould ſpring up ſome <hi>Root of Bitterneſs in our ſouls,</hi> and cauſe us to depart from the living God, and grieve his holy Spirit with our evil wayes, and give him occaſion to ſwear in his wrath, That <hi>we ſhall never enter into this Heavenly Reſt;</hi> for it is not every one that begins well, But <hi>he that endures to the END ſhall be ſaved;</hi> not every one that follows Jeſus Chriſt for a little ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſo leave Him, that ſhall receive the Reward, <hi>But he that continues and abideth faithful unto DEATH, ſhall receive the Crown of Life;</hi> it is not every one that begins to fight well, that ſhall obtain the prize, <hi>But he that overcometh ſhall inherit all things.</hi> Therefore <hi>let us take heed that we do not grow weary of well doing, and ſo faint be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we Reap:</hi> Neither let us give place to the Devil, leſt he deprive
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97238:30"/>us of our Eternal Harveſt, and plunder us of our Heavenly Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but let us continue and perſevere all our dayes in the work and ſervice of our Heavenly Father, and never turn again unto fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for Alas, we had better never begin well, except we continue ſo, and end well; <hi>For if after we have eſcaped the pollutions of the world, through the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt, we are again intangled therein and overcome, then our latter end will be worſe than our begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; for it had been better for us, never to have KNOWN the way of Righteouſneſs, than after we have known it, to turn from the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment delivered unto us,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20, 21. Therefore now let us take our laſt leave of every evil work, and wholly apply our ſelves to the work and ſervice of God, and make it our meat and drink to do the Will of our Heavenly Father: And as the Lord hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led us to a Heavenly Kingdom, ſo let us exerciſe our ſelves in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things, and be no more in love with the beggerly things of this life, but let us alwayes be found acting ſuitable to our Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and walking in ſuch wayes as become thoſe that are Heirs of a Glorious Kingdom, confeſſing that we are but Strangers and Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims here on earth, having our affections eſtranged from the things of this world; That we may declare plainly, that here we have no continuing City, but we ſeek one to come, that ſo in all things we may dignifie our Heavenly Profeſſion, and walk worthy of God, who hath called us to his Kingdom and Glory, alwayes remembring the counſel of the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Wherefore we receiving a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which cannot be moved; let us hold faſt Grace, whereby we may ſerve God acceptably with reverence and godly fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for the ſecond <hi>Uſe,</hi> by way of Examination, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt with a word of Caution.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Thirdly,</hi> by way of Encouragement.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Uſe.</hi> Is it ſo, that the Lord is pleaſed to provide and prepare ſuch a Glorious Kingdom for his People? Oh then, this may mightily encourage us to hold out in a time of Tryal, and to continue faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for God in a ſuffering day. Oh! the conſideration of this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Reward may exceedingly ſupport us under Sufferings, and make us valiant for God in a day of Trouble, and ballance all oppoſitions whatſoever; for whatever we ſuffer or undergo for Chriſt, will be nothing in compariſon of the Glory that ſhall be revealed for us in this Heavenly Kingdom: whatever we loſe for Chriſt, ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly rewarded with great advantage; whatever difficulties we
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97238:31"/>are expoſed unto for God, ſhall be wonderfully requited in this Kingdom of Glory. Oh! how may this bear up our ſouls in Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and make us rejoyce under all our ſufferings? Oh! how may this greatly encourage us to run with patience the Race that is ſet before us, and lightly eſteem the ſtorms and ſtyles that lye in our way? for conſider, What can we ſuffer here, that is worth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, if we compare it with this Recompence of Reward? Art thou in Trouble? well be content, it is but for a while, and this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom will eaſe thee, and thou ſhalt never be in Trouble any more. Art thou in Sorrow? well, endeavour to be cheerful, remember, <hi>in thy Fathers Kingdom there is fulneſs of Joy,</hi> and there thou ſhalt be eternally happy. Art thou deprived of worldly poſſeſſions, and ſo expoſed to hunger and want? well, be of good cheer, ſtill thou art Heir to a Heavenly Kingdom, and there thou ſhalt never hunger any more. Art thou in danger of loſing thy life for the ſake of Chriſt? well, be it ſo, part with it freely, this Kingdom will make amends for all, thou ſhalt be ſure to find it again, and be crowned with Life Eternal. Oh! who then would part with this Heavenly Kingdom for a little outward eaſe and bodily advantage, which may laſt but for a day? who then would leave and forſake this Eternal Reward, to avoid a little temporal Trouble, and turn their backs upon a Glorious Kingdom, to eſcape a few light afflictions? Who then would change this infinite Portion, for a little trifling vanity, and ſell this eternal Inheritance for that which profiteth not? but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let's be encouraged to continue faithful in our Teſtimony for God, whatever it may coſt us; and let's lift up our heads with Joy, and be exceeding cheerful under all our perſecuting Troubles? for whatever our condition is, yet ſtill our Kingdom-Portion remains firm and ſure without corruption, and can never be taken away from us, unleſs we deprive our ſelves of it, by our ſinning againſt the Lord.</p>
            <p>You ſhall find, that this very conſideration did exceedingly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the primitive Chriſtians in the Apoſtles dayes, to hold out with joy under all their ſufferings: ſee that notable inſtance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.32, 33, 34. where the Apoſtle is putting of them in mind of their former great and grievous ſufferings, and commending of them for their excellent behaviour under them: <hi>But call to remembrance</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>the former dayes, in which after ye were illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ye endured a great fight of afflictions, partly whilſt ye were made a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97238:31"/>gazing-ſtock, both by reproaches and afflictions; and partly whilſt ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came companions of them that were ſo uſed; for ye had compaſſion of me in my bonds, and took joyfully the ſpoyling of your goods.</hi> Here was a great ſtorm of afflictions, and abundance of ſufferings, that befel theſe poor primitive Chriſtians in their journey towards Heaven. Here were mockings and reproaches, and many other afflictions, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with plundering and ſpoyling of goods; and yet they were ſo far from being diſcouraged at theſe things, as that they did not only take them patiently, but joyfully: Why, what was the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that theſe Chriſtians were ſo joyful under their ſufferings, and ſo much ſupported and encouraged under all their afflictions? why this was the buſineſs: They knew in themſelves that in HEAVEN they had a BETTER and an ENDURING Subſtance; They knew that though they were Loſers now, yet they ſhould be great Gainers in the Kingdom of Heaven; They knew that there was a Reward laid up for them in Heaven, which would abundantly make them amends for all their loſſes and ſufferings here; They knew that their Portion in Heaven was unmoveable, and nothing could ſpoyl that eternal Inheritance: Therefore they did not value the loſs of any thing here below, ſo long as they had an intereſt in ſuch a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly-enduring Subſtance.</p>
            <p>See alſo the example of <hi>Moſes,</hi> where it is notably laid down for our encouragement, under this very conſideration, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.24, 25, 26. <hi>Who when he was come to years, refuſed to be called the ſon of</hi> Pharoah's <hi>daughter; chuſing rather to ſuffer afflictions with the People of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon.</hi> (Mark) He left and forſook all the pleaſures of <hi>Pharoah's</hi> Court, and denyed the Princely promotion of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and made a voluntary choice of a ſuffering path, with deſpiſed People, rather than a pleaſant Paſture, with honourable Society; <hi>Eſteeming the Reproach of Chriſt greater Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches than the Treaſures of</hi> Egypt; when he might have enjoyed great honour and dignity in the Court of a King, <hi>he chuſed rather ſhame and reproach,</hi> in a ſuffering Wilderneſs, and accounted that the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt choice, and the greateſt happineſs. Why, what was the reaſon of all this? what was the matter with <hi>Moſes,</hi> that he did ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully chuſe to ſuffer afflictions, when he might have en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyed his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and content himſelf with ſhame and reproach, when he might have enjoyed great honour and dignity? Why here was the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fineſs: <hi>FOR</hi> (ſayes the Text) <hi>he had reſpect unto the RECOM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PENCE
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97238:32"/>of REWARD.</hi> He had ſuch a love to the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that he did not value the Treaſures of <hi>Egypt;</hi> he had ſuch an eye to the Reward in heaven, that he did not matter the pleaſures on earth; for he knew, and did believe that all things ſhould work together for his good and great advantage, and that he ſhould be abundantly requited in this Heavenly Kingdom: Therefore ſo long as he kept up his intereſt there, he had more comfort in ſuffering afflictions, than he could have had in the enjoyment of all the world without it; for the leaſt Branch of this Heavenly Happineſs, is better worth than all the pleaſures under the Sun: Therefore the conſideration of this Heavenly Reward, did make him deny his earthly Glory and Dignity, and did mightily bear up his ſoul in the midſt of ſufferings.</p>
            <p>Yea further, let me tell you; this very Conſideration was a great ſupport even unto our Saviour Chriſt himſelf under all his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and a great comfort to him in all his ſufferings; therefore we are exhorted to conſider his example, and to make him our pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern in this very particular, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2, 3. where the Apoſtle bids us, <hi>Look unto Jeſus the Author and finiſher of our Faith; who for the JOY that was ſet before him, endured the Croſs, and deſpiſed the ſhame, and is now ſet down at the right hand of the Throne of God.</hi> (Mark) The JOY that was ſet before him, and the Crown that was laid up for him, was that which did exceedingly bear up his Soul to endure the Croſs, and carry him forth to deſpiſe the Shame; for he knew, that though he was attended with ſorrows here on Earth, yet there was joy enough in Heaven to make him amends for all: And though he was now cloathed with ſhame and reproach, yet he ſhould ſhortly be cloathed with Glory and Majeſty in his Fathers King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and for his Croſs he ſhould receive a Heavenly Crown: Therefore he willingly bore the Croſs, and patiently underwent the Reproach, knowing that this Glorious Reward would largely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite him for all his Troubles: Therefore ſayes the Apoſtle; <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider him that endured ſuch contradiction of ſinners againſt himſelf, leſt ye be wearied, and faint in your minds.</hi> When we are ſurrounded with Sorrow, and compaſſed about with Troubles, let's remember our Heavenly Portion, where we ſhall have fulneſs of joy and pleaſures for ever; and when we are attended with croſſes and ſeveral cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, then let's remember our Crown of Glory, reſerved for us in our Fathers Kingdom: Let us in all things conſider the example
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97238:32"/>of Jeſus Chriſt, and be ſure to follow his ſteps; and then we ſhall be ſure to partake of the ſame encouragement, and be in a better ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to run with patience the Race that is ſet before us.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the third <hi>Uſe,</hi> by way of Encouragement.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Fourthly,</hi> by way of Exhortation; this may ſerve to exhort us to three things:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Seeing it is ſo, That the Lord hath ſo much tender love and reſpect for his People, as to provide and prepare a Kingdom for them: Oh! then let us be exhorted to increaſe and abound in our love one towards another: Let us be ſure to continue ſtedfaſt in Brotherly Love, and to abound in Chriſtian charity one towards another, as becomes the Elect of God; for if the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf have ſuch Bowels of Love and Affection for them, as to honour them with a Crown and Kingdom; how much more ſhould we have Bowels of Love and affection one towards another, for whom this Kingdom is provided? And if the Lord himſelf tender his People as the Apple of his Eye, and count them worthy of Eternal Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Oh! how may this engage us to be tender one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and count one another worthy of reſpect and love? yea, it may engage us to manifeſt abundance of tender love, and cordial affection, even to the meaneſt and pooreſt of the Lords People; yea, though they be never ſo contemptible in the eyes of the World, and never ſo mean and low in their earthly ſtations, yet let us be tender towards them, and embrace them in love, and let us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them honourable, and eſteem them lovely; for they are all Heirs of a Glorious Kingdom, and they are all the dearly Beloved of the Lord: Therefore this may engage us to love one another, and this may engage us to be exceeding careful of each others welfare: Therefore ſayes the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Beloved, if God ſo loved us, how ought we to love one another?</hi> If the Lord himſelf hath ſo much love for us, as to make us heirs of life and glory; how ſhould this enjoyn us to endeavour to exceed in our love one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, and to abound in our affections towards all Saints? Oh! let us take heed of ſlighting and contemning one another, and let us take heed of ſcorning and ſetting at nought, even the very pooreſt and meaneſt of Gods Jewels: But let all thoſe that truly fear the Lord, be dear and precious to us, though they are never ſo vile and ridiculous in the account of the World; for they are all lovely in the ſight of God, and they are all precious in the eyes of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97238:33"/>the Lord; and we are all his Children by faith in Jeſus Chriſt; therefore let us live in unity and love like Brethren; Let us get and maintain an affection ſuitable to our Spiritual Relation, and be ſure to diſcharge a tender duty one towards another; for we are all Children of one Father, and we are all fed from one Fountain, and we all belong to one Family, and we are all Heirs to one Kingdom: Therefore let us take heed of dividing in our Love, and of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in Affection; ſeeing we are all one in Spiritual Relation, and all concern'd in one Portion; and ſeeing we are all travelling to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards one Country, and all journying towards one Land: Oh! let us take heed that we do not quarrel and fall out by the way; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let us like honeſt Travellers, love and pitty one another, and comfort and encourage one another, and bear one anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and help one another forward in our progreſs towards Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; that ſo we may manifeſt our ſelves to be the Children of God, and the Diſciples of Chriſt, by our love and affection one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another; and that we may make it appear to the world, that we are living Chriſtians, by our love to Chriſtians; and that we are Born of God, by our love to his Begotten: for ſayes the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.14. <hi>We know that we have paſſed from Death to Life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we love the Brethren; for he that loveth not his Brother abideth in Death.</hi> (Mark) He that hath not love and affection towards his Chriſtian Brethren, it is an evident ſign that he is in a ſtate of Death, and that he is very unfit to ſtand as a Member in the Church of Chriſt; for he is of no more uſe there, than a rotten Branch in a fruitful Tree, or a wooden legg in a mans Body, which ſtands only for an outward ſhew, but hath no life in it to refreſh the Body; and if all the members of the Body ſhould be afflicted with grief, yet ſtill that would feel no pain, nor would not at all be ſenſible of the Bodies ſufferings; and the reaſon is, becauſe it's a dead mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and wants the life that maintains and feeds the Body: even ſo it is with a profeſſed Chriſtian that wants love to his Brethren; he can hear of the afflictions of his Brethren, and not at all be troubled; and he can underſtand that his Brethren are in great want and miſery, and have no ſympathy nor fellow-feeling with them in their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and the reaſon is, becauſe he is a dead member, and wants that ſpiritual life that feeds and maintains the power of Godlineſs in the Soul; for if he be acquainted with the Spiritual Birth, and if his Soul be alive for God, he cannot be without love to his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97238:33"/>Therefore ſayes the Apoſtle in another place: <hi>Beloved, let us love one another, for love is of God; and every one that loveth his Brother is Born of God,</hi> and is acquainted with the Lord. Therefore let this Doctrine of the Kingdom perſwade us to continue and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in this fruit of the Spirit; and ſeeing we profeſs our ſelves to be all Partners in one Kingdom, let us be all Partners together in Love and Affection.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the firſt word of Exhortation.</p>
            <p>But again, <hi>Secondly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If it be ſo, that the Lord hath provided and prepared a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for his People, and will one day Crown them with Eternal Glory: Oh! then let us be exhorted to bleſs and praiſe the Lord for his goodneſs towards us, and to magnifie his Glorious Name for this his unſpeakable Love. Oh! the exceeding Riches of his Grace in this very particular, doth mightily engage us to celebrate his praiſe to the utmoſt of our power, both in word and action: Oh! how are we bound to ſet forth his Glory, and to magnifie his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and to ſpeak well of his Goodneſs, for this his tender reſpect to his People: yea, all his Attributes ſhines and ſhews themſelves beautifully in the accompliſhment of this our great and wonderful Priviledge, and loudly calls for a thankful Return at our hands. Oh! how are we engaged to the Lord for his Goodneſs? and how are we bound to praiſe him for his rich Grace? To conſider, that we, even ſuch poor Creatures as we, even when we were in a loſt periſhing ſtate, &amp; lay polluted in our Blood, in an undone Condition, that then the Lord ſhould vouchſafe to caſt his Eye upon us, and pitty us, and manifeſt his Love and Goodneſs ſo far unto our Souls, as to find out a way for our Recovery, and to bring about our Redemption by the death of his own Son, and to put us into a capacity of Salvation, that we might be honoured with the Dignity of Adoption, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to call him Father, through faith in his only Begotten; That ſo we might be partakers of a Heavenly, Glorious, and Unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Kingdom. Oh! what unſpeakable Love, and excellent Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is this? Oh! what rich Grace, and infinite Mercy is here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to our Souls? How do we ſtand engaged to the Lord for his infinite Goodneſs? Pray let's conſider how it is in natural Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: If in caſe, that we were poor and miſerable, and wanted relief and comfort for our outward Man, and could not tell where, nor which way to find any ſuccour: And now if a rich Man that hath
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97238:34"/>fulneſs about him, ſhould take our Condition into conſideration, and meerly out of Love and Pitty towards us, ſhould hand forth Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and Comfort to us, and plentifully ſupply all our Wants, and put us into a happy Condition, and after all this, make us Heirs of a Rich Inheritance. Oh! how ſhould we be engaged to eſteem ſuch a Courteſie as this? And how ſhould we be engaged to prize ſuch a wonderful Kindneſs? Oh! how would this bind us to acknowledge his Love, and draw forth our hearts with thankfulneſs towards him? Or elſe, if we did not, almoſt every one would be ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn us for our Ingratitude: And beſides, we ſhould even give our Friend juſt occaſion to caſt us out of his favour, and take our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance from us. Well, but now the Lord hath done abundance more for us than all this, and he hath extended his Love towards us in a wonderful manner, even beyond compariſon: yea, he hath done that for us, that all the men in the World, and all the Angels in Heaven, could never have done by their greateſt power; and he hath provided and prepared ſuch a Rich and Glorious Portion for us, as all the World is not comparable thereunto.</p>
            <p>Oh! then conſider, how are we bound to prize and eſteem this infinite Kindneſs of God, and thankfully to acknowledge his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Love? And how are we bound to bleſs the Lord for his Goodneſs, and to ſhew forth the Praiſes of him who hath thus cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led us out of Darkneſs, into his marvellous Light? Therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord hath been ſo much enlarged in his Love and Goodneſs towards us: Oh! let us endeavour to be enlarged in our thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards him, leſt we give him occaſion to withdraw his Love from us for our groſs Ingratitude, and deprive us of our Portion, for our ill improvement of his great Love: Therefore you ſhall find that the Apoſtle himſelf makes this uſe of this very particular, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3, 4. <hi>Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which according to his abundant Mercy hath Begotten us again unto a lively hope, by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the Dead, to an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance incorruptible and undefiled, which fadeth not away, reſerved in Heaven for us.</hi> (Mark) The conſideration of Gods Goodneſs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in our hope of Glory, and the conſideration of our reſerved Inheritance, is that which doth here occaſion him to bleſs and praiſe the Lord, and exceedingly draws forth his ſpirit with thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs towards him, and cauſeth him to acknowledge and admire his abundant Mercy towards us; who hath Begotten us to a lively
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97238:34"/>hope of ſuch a Heavenly Inheritance; Therefore ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Col.</hi> 1.12, 13. <hi>We do not ceaſe to give thanks unto the Father, which hath made us meet to be partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light; who hath delivered us from the power of Darkneſs, and hath tranſlated us into the Kingdom of his dear Son.</hi> Oh! therefore let the conſideration of our Heavenly Portion dwell upon our hearts, and exceedingly draw forth our ſouls with thankfulneſs towards our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father; and let us mightily endeavour to ſet forth the Praiſe and Glory of him, who hath provided and prepared ſuch an Excellent Kingdom for his People.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the ſecond word of Exhortation.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now come to the Third and laſt word of Exhortation, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Seeing the Lord hath provided and prepared ſuch a Glorious and Heavenly Kingdom for his People; Oh! then let all thoſe that profeſſe an Intereſt in this Kingdom, walk worthy of God, who hath called us to ſuch a Glorious Inheritance: Let the conſideration thereof mightily engage us to a Holy, and a Heavenly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. Oh! let us be ſure to walk ſuitably and anſwerably to ſuch an Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and Heavenly Profeſſion; as becomes thoſe that are Heirs of a Kingdom, and as becomes thoſe that have an Intereſt in ſuch an unſpeakable Portion: Oh! let's conſider what a Glorious Profeſſion we bear, and what a Heavenly work we are called unto; and let us be ſure to walk ſo, as that we may honour our Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with a ſuitable Converſation, and anſwer the end of our Heavenly Calling, by a cheerful continuing in the paths of Holineſs. Oh! let us take heed that our Actions do not witneſs againſt our Words, and our Converſations give our Profeſſion the lye; But as we bear a Heavenly Profeſſion, ſo let us lead a Heavenly Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; and let us not ſuffer our hearts and affections to run out after the things of this Life; <hi>But if we be riſen with Chriſt, let us ſeek thoſe things which are above,</hi> and ſet our Affections there where we profeſs our Portion is; and let us manifeſt our ſelves to be Heirs of this Kingdom, by our conſtant continuing in the work of the Kingdom; and let us not ſhame our ſelves, nor diſgrace our Royal Profeſſion with doring upon the beggerly things of this World; but let us make it appear to the World, that we are the Sons of God, and Heirs of Heaven, by abounding in the fruits of the Spirit, and devoting our ſelves to Heavenly things; and let us take heed that we do not defile our ſelves with any of the works of Darkneſs, nor ſtain our Heavenly Reputation with wandring in the filthy paths of Iniquity: For we that profeſs our ſelves to be Heirs of this Glorious Kingdom, we muſt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to walk as other Gentiles walk, <hi>in the vanity of their minds, and in the luſts of the fleſh;</hi> (for if we do, we muſt expect to be rewarded accordingly) But we muſt if we expect a better Reward than others, exerciſe our ſelves in a better Work than others; and we muſt put off our former Converſation, and caſt away the old Man with his deeds, which is corrupt, and be renewed in the Spirit of our Minds, and put on the new Man, which after God is created, in Righteouſneſs &amp; true Holineſs, that ſo we may adorn our Princely Profeſsion, and walk worthy of the Vocation wherewith we are Called. For pray conſider, what an unſuitable thing it would be for a Prince, or one that is Heir to an Earthly Kingdom, to go up and down in Beggers Apparel, and aſſociate himſelf with the meaneſt and baſeſt of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and expoſe himſelf to ſuch a contemptible Courſe of life, as to ſpend his time in the works of drudgery and ſlaviſh employment, and take up his lodging (with Beggers) on a dunghil, or under a hedge; and yet keep up his Princely Profeſsion, and proclaim himſelf to be the Son of a King, and Heir to a Kingdom; I ſay it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97238:35"/>would be accounted a very unſuitable thing, and a great diſhonour to one of his degree, and it would very much ſtain and diminiſh his Reputation in the eyes of the World, and render him very ridiculous amongſt his Friends and Relations: How much more would it be an unſuitable thing for us that profeſſe our ſelves to be the Children of GOD, and Princes of HEAVEN, and Heirs to an ETER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAL Kingdom, if we ſhould ſuffer the rags of unrighteouſneſs to reſt upon us, and go along with the wicked in the paths of impurity, and exerciſe our ſelves in the Devils drudgery, and ſet our affections upon the unprofitable dunghils of this Life, &amp; take up our lodging here under the hedges of Earthly Vanity; Oh! how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable would it be to our Heavenly Profeſsion? And how greatly would it derogate from God, and diminiſh the Reputation of Godlineſs? And how unworthy and unfit ſhould we render our ſelves of ſuch a Glorious Inheritance: and we ſhould cauſe the way of Truth to be mightily abuſed, and manifeſt our ſelves to be no better than Hypocrites: Therefore now let us endeavour to regulate and order our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations aright, in the fear of the Lord, and to walk circumſpectly, both in Words and Actions, redeeming the time, becauſe the dayes are evil; and let no cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Communication proceed out of our mouths, nor no corrupt Actions be ſeen in our lives, but rather let the appearance of Gods Grace unto our Souls, teach as to deny ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly and righteouſly in this preſent evil World, that ſo we may walk worthy of the Lord unto all pleaſing, increaſing and abounding in the fruits of the Spirit, and continuing and perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the way of the Lord, all the dayes of our lives, to the Praiſe and Glory of him, who hath called us to ſuch a Heavenly, Glorious, unmoveable Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Now the God of Peace, that brought again from the dead our Lord Jeſus, that great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the blood of the Everlaſting Covenant; make us perfect in every good Work to do his Will, working in us that which is well-pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord; To whom with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, through the Spirit of Grace, be Bleſsing and Glory, Wiſdom and Thankſgiving, Honour and Power, Might, Majeſty, and Dominion, now, henceforth and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97238:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
